HOMELAND OF THE RAMA TO SALONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE
INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH
THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAMAKRISHNA LONI HAVE NEVER
CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE
RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELAND. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAW
MATERIAL OWNING COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE SINCE AMERICA STANDS ONE NATION THIS INDIVISIBLE.
>> ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I'D LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF
AT PACIFIC OF TV AND TODAY THAT IS PARTICULARLY KALEENA
MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL YOUR
ATTENDANCE HERE IN PERSON IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE
CHAMBER ROOM 2 TO 50 SECOND FLOOR OF CITY HALL.
>> AND WHEN YOU ARE NOT ABLE TO BE HERE YOU CAN CATCH THE
PROCEEDING. IT IS AIRING LIVE ON S.F. GOVEE
TV'S CHANNEL 26 OR THE LIVE STREAM AT W W W DOT S.F. GEO
VTV.ORG. IF YOU HAVE PUBLIC COMMENT THAT
YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT IN WRITING EITHER SENDING AN
EMAIL TO BOSS AT S.F. CAVALIERE OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE JUST
ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B GOOD LIT PLACE CITY HALL ROOM
244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102 IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A
REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR A FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE
AMERICANS WITH DISABILITY ACT OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE
ASSISTANCE PLEASE CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO
BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184.
AND AS STATED PREVIOUSLY PURSUANT TO A MEMO DATED APRIL
7TH, 2026 FROM SUPERVISOR JACKIE FIELDER, A MOTION WE'RE
RENEWING IT EVERY WEEK BETWEEN APRIL 7TH AND JUNE 30TH 2026 TO
EXCUSE SUPERVISOR FIELDER FROM THE CURRENT MEETING.
>> THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT AND MEMBERS THANK YOU MADAM
CLERK. I NOTICE THAT SUPERVISOR DORSEY
IS IN THE QUEUE. >> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT
MANDOLIN I WANT TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE TO OUR CLERK FOR
WELCOMING TODAY'S VIEWERS AND I WANTED TO ADD MY OWN SPECIAL
WELCOME TO THE CLASS FROM SIV LAB HOW SAN FRANCISCO
GOVERNMENT WORKS AND EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE TO DISTRICT SIX
RESIDENT MICHAEL ADAMS FOR LEADING THAT EFFORT.
SO I JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU TO ALL OF YOU FOR YOUR CIVIC
ENGAGEMENT AND WELCOME TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> CHAMBERS THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND WELCOME.
ALL RIGHT. >> SO CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO
EXCUSE SUPERVISOR FIELDER FROM TODAY'S MEETING?
A MOTION MADE BY SUPERVISOR CHEN SECONDED BY SUPERVISE OR
MELGAR AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION
AND WITHOUT OBJECTION. >> SUPERVISOR FIELD IS EXCUSED
. >> AND THEN MADAM CLERK, LET'S
GO TO APPROVAL OF MEETING MINUTES.
>> YES. APPROVAL OF THE MEETING MINUTES
DATED MARCH 24TH 2026. >> CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO
APPROVE THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVE BY WALTON IS
THERE A SECONDED BY CHEN? >> MADAM CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WILTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG
WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANDEL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I AND SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR EITHER A ATTORNEYS WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT
AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA PLEASE
CALL ITEMS ONE THROUGH FIVE TOGETHER ITEMS ONE THROUGH FIVE
ARE ON CONSENT. >> THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED
ROUTINE. IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY
BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY PLEASE CALL THE ROLL
ON ITEMS ONE THROUGH FIVE SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANAGEMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I THERE ARE CHINESE
WITHOUT OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER SIX ITEM SIX THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO EXTEND FOR
AN ADDITIONAL FIVE YEARS THROUGH JULY 1ST 2031 THE
DELEGATION OF BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AUTHORITY UNDER
CHARTER SECTION 9.118 TO THE GENERAL MANAGER OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION PREVIOUSLY
AUTHORIZED BY ORDINANCE NUMBER 26 DASH 19 AND EXTENDED
AND MODIFIED BY ORDINANCE NUMBERS 101 DASH 2159 DASH 22
AND 207 DASH 24 TO ENTER INTO GRANT AGREEMENTS UNDER THE AS
OF PARKS GREEN INFRASTRUCTURE GRANT PROGRAM WITH 20 YEAR
TERMS AFTER THE PROJECT COMPLETION DATE.
>> ALL RIGHT, LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE ORDINANCES FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER SEVEN.
ITEM SEVEN THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ZONING MAP OF THE
PLANNING CODE TO CHANGE THE HEIGHT AND BULK DISTRICTS FOR
THE ONE OAK STREET PROJECT TO INCREASE THE ALLOWED HEIGHT FOR
THE PODIUM OF THE BUILDING AND THE CURRENT BASE HEIGHT
LIMIT OF 120FT TO 140FT AND TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS AGAIN.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCES FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEMS EIGHT AND NINE TOGETHER ITEMS EIGHT AND NINE ARE TWO
ORDINANCES ESTABLISHING ENTERTAINMENT ZONES FOR ITEM
EIGHT. THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND
THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO CREATE THE GLEN PARK
ENTERTAINMENT ZONE ON DIAMOND STREET BETWEEN MONTERREY
BOULEVARD AND HENRY STREET CANNERY STREET BETWEEN BROMPTON
AVENUE AND CAREY STREET MONTEREY BOULEVARD BETWEEN
DIAMOND STREET AND JUICED AVENUE AND KERN STREET BETWEEN
BROMPTON AVENUE AND DIAMOND STREET.
AND FOR ITEM NINE, THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO CREATE THE UPPER FILLMORE
ENTERTAINMENT ZONE ON FILLMORE STREET FROM JACKSON TO SUTTER
STREETS CALIFORNIA STREET FROM FILLMORE STREET TO STEINER'S
STREET AND PINE STREET FROM FILLMORE STREET TO STEINER
STREET. AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE AND MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS FOR BOTH ITEMS AND WE CAN TAKE THESE SAME HOUSE SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE AUDIENCES ARE FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL OUT A NUMBER TEN ITEM TEN THIS IS
AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO
ESTABLISH THE PACIFIC ISLANDER CULTURAL DISTRICT IN AND AROUND
THE VISITATION VALLEY AND SUNNYDALE NEIGHBORHOODS TO
REQUIRE THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT TO SUBMIT WRITTEN REPORTS AND RECOMMENDATIONS TO
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE MAYOR TO DESCRIBE THE
CULTURAL ATTRIBUTES OF THE DISTRICT AND TO PROPOSE
STRATEGIES TO ACKNOWLEDGE AND PRESERVE THE CULTURAL
LEGACY OF THE DISTRICT AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 11 ITEM 11 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO RETROACTIVELY
AUTHORIZE THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND AN APPROXIMATE $6.25 MILLION GRANT FROM THE U.S.
DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE OFFICE OF COMMUNITY ORIENTED POLICING
SERVICES AS COPS UNDER THE FISCAL YEAR 2025 COPS HIRING
PROGRAM TO FUND 50 NEW POLICE OFFICER POSITIONS FOR
APPROXIMATELY ONE YEAR OCTOBER 1ST 2025 THROUGH SEPTEMBER 30TH
2030 AND TO AMEND THE ANNUAL SALARY ORDINANCE NUMBER 120
DASH 25 FOR FISCAL YEARS 2025 THROUGH 26 AND 26 THROUGH 2027
TO PROVIDE FOR THE ADDITION OF 50 GRANT FUNDED POSITIONS
IN CLASS Q002 POLICE OFFICER CHAIR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT
AMENDMENT I JUST WANT TO THANK MY COLLEAGUES INCLUDING
SUPERVISOR CHEN WHO SUBSTITUTE FOR ME AT THE COMMITTEE LAST
WEEK ON THESE ITEMS COMING OUT OF BUDGET AND FINANCE
COMMITTEE. BUT JUST BEFORE I AM AND I
THINK THAT IT WAS INDICATED IN THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE
ANALYST REPORT BUT I JUST WANT TO BE ON THE RECORD ABOUT ITEM
11 AS THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT IS ACCEPTING THIS
GRANT FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE SPECIFICALLY FOR OUR
LAW ENFORCEMENT FOR THIS 50 FULL TIME POSITION THAT IT DOES
NOT AND I WANT TO JUST ON THE RECORD BY TO BE A BE ON THE
RECORD VERIFYING THIS IS THAT BY ACCEPTING THIS GRANT IS NOT
IN ANY FORM COMMITMENT COMMITTING THE CITY THAT THE
CITY IS STILL IN COMMITTED AND BE ABLE TO COMPLY NS BY
ACCEPTING THIS GRANDE FOR OUR SANCTUARY CITY LAW OR MAYBE THE
CITY ATTORNEY CAN VERIFY DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD ROSS
SUPERVISOR CHAN THIS GRANT IS AT ISSUE IN THE LITIGATION THAT
OUR OFFICE BROUGHT CHALLENGING THE CONDITIONS THAT THE
DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE HAS ATTEMPTED TO PLACE ON IT
CURRENTLY THOSE CONDITIONS WHERE WE PREVAILED SO FAR
IN THAT LITIGATION AND THERE'S A PRELIMINARY INJUNCTION
IN PLACE THAT PREVENTS THE CITY FROM HAVING TO COMPLY WITH THE
CONDITIONS THAT WE'RE CONTESTING.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU CHAIR CHAN THANK YOU
BRAD RUSSI AND WITH THAT I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING AND MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEMS 12 THROUGH 14 TOGETHER ITEM 12 THROUGH 14 ARE THREE
ORDINANCES THAT ADOPT AND IMPLEMENT MEMORANDUM OF
UNDERSTANDING BETWEEN THE CITY AND COUNTY AND THE FOLLOWING
DEPARTMENTS FOR ITEM 12 THIS IS WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
OFFICERS ASSOCIATION. ITEM 13 IS WITH THE SAN
FRANCISCO FIREFIGHTERS UNION LOCAL 798 A UNIT TO AIR FFA,
AFL CIO AND ITEM 14 IS WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE FIGHTERS
UNION LOCAL 790 8IFF AFL-CIO UNIT ONE FOR THESE ITEMS 12
THROUGH 14 TO BE EFFECTIVE JULY FIRST 2026 THROUGH JUNE 30TH
2030 AND WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 15 ITEM 15 THIS IS
A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF
PROPERTY TO AMEND THE LEASE OF A PORTION OF REAL PROPERTY
LOCATED AT 845 JACKSON STREET ON THE FOURTH FLOOR WITH THE
CHINESE HOSPITAL ASSOCIATION SERVING AS THE TEMPORARY
LOCATION OF A DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH CHINATOWN PUBLIC
HEALTH CENTER TO CHANGE THE LEASE EXPIRATION DATE FROM
OCTOBER 29TH, 2028 TO THE THIRD YEAR ANNIVERSARY OF THE DATE OF
THE ISSUANCE OF A CHANGE OF USE PERMIT BY THE STATE OF
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH CARE ACCESS AND INFORMATION TO
INCREASE THE CONSTRUCTION TO LEASEHOLD IMPROVEMENTS
REIMBURSEMENT ALLOWANCE BY AN AMOUNT OF 500,000 FOR A NEW
TOTAL MAXIMUM AMOUNT OF 800,000 AND I THINK WE COULD TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
16 THROUGH 19 TOGETHER. >> ITEM 16 THROUGH 19 ARE FOR
RESOLUTIONS THAT APPROVE THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING
AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO APPLY FOR ACCEPT AND EXPEND
PROGRAM ENTITLEMENTS FROM THE UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF
HOUSING AND URBAN DEVELOPMENT FOR ITEM 16 THIS IS FOR THE
CITY'S FISCAL YEAR 26 THROUGH 27 CDBG PROGRAM ENTITLEMENT FOR
19.3 MILLION AND TO EXPEND ESTIMATED PROGRAM INCOME IN THE
AMOUNT OF 2.1 MILLION FOR A COMBINED TOTAL OF APPROXIMATELY
21.5 MILLION BEGINNING JULY 1ST 2026 THROUGH THE DATE WHEN ALL
FUNDS ARE EXPENDED FOR ITEM 17 THIS IS FOR THE CITY'S FISCAL
YEAR 20 2627 HOME PROGRAM ENTITLEMENT IN THE COMBINED
TOTAL APPROXIMATE AMOUNT OF 6.6 MILLION FOR THE TERM JULY 1ST
2026 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2031 FOR ITEM 18 THIS IS FOR THE CITY'S
FISCAL YEAR 2627 ESG PROGRAM ENTITLEMENT OF 1.7 MILLION FOR
AN UNSPECIFIED TERM STARTING JULY 1ST, 2026 AND FOR ITEM 19
THIS IS FOR THE CITY'S 2627 HARBOR PROGRAM ENTITLEMENT
IN THE AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 7.. 4 MILLION AND TO EXPAND
PROGRAM INCOME AND REPROGRAMED FUNDS IN THE AMOUNT OF 202,000
FOR A COMBINED TOTAL OF APPROXIMATE 7.7 MILLION FOR THE
TERM JULY 1ST 2025 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2029 AND WE'LL TAKE THESE
SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER 20 ITEM 20. THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO ACCEPT
THE SHERIFF'S OFFICE MILITARY EQUIPMENT USE POLICY 2025
ANNUAL REPORT AND INVENTORY AND TO APPROVE THEIR REQUEST
FOR PURCHASE AND USE OF ADDITIONAL EQUIPMENT CONSISTENT
WITH THE CRITERIA SET FORTH IN STATE LAW.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT IS THE
SHERIFF HERE YET OR A REPRESENTATIVE?
IF NOT, I WOULD LIKE TO ASK THAT WE COME BACK TO THIS ITEM
BECAUSE HE TOLD ME HE WOULD BE HE ALSO INDICATED TO ME THAT HE
WOULD BE HERE FOR THIS ITEM SO WE WILL WE WILL COME BACK TO
ITEM 20. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK,
PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 21. >> ITEM 21 THIS IS A MOTION TO
DIRECT THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST TO
INITIATE A PERFORMANCE AUDIT IN 2026 FOR THE SHERIFF'S
OFFICE. >> >> I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE MOTION IS APPROVED. >> ALL RIGHT.
AND LET'S GO BACK TO ITEM 20. ITEM 28.
FOR THOSE OF YOU WHO JUST ENTERED THE CHAMBER, IT IS ON
THE FLOOR. IT'S A RESOLUTION TO ACCEPT THE
SHERIFF'S OFFICE MILITARY EQUIPMENT USE POLICY 2025.
>> ALL RIGHT. WELCOME, SHERIFF MIYAMOTO.
COME ON UP. SUPERVISOR WALTON HAS
QUESTIONS. COMMENTS.
SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
AND THANK YOU, SHERIFF MIYAMOTO.
I'M PART OF APPROVAL OF THIS IS ALLOWING FOR POSSIBLE
ADDITIONAL EQUIPMENT IS THAT ADDITIONAL EQUIPMENT SOMETHING
THAT IS IDENTIFIED ALREADY OR THIS IS JUST A BLINK SAYING IF
YOU WANT SOME MORE EQUIPMENT WE ARE POSSIBLY APPROVING THAT
WITHOUT KNOWING WHAT IT IS. >> GOOD AFTERNOON AND THANK YOU
FOR THE OPPORTUNITY TO ANSWER THAT QUESTION.
IT IS NOT A BLANK IN ANY WAY, SHAPE OR FORM TO SPECIFIC ITEMS
THAT ARE BEING REQUESTED RIGHT NOW AS NEW EQUIPMENT.
THEY'RE LISTED ON THERE. ONE IS A DESIRE FOR A DRONE FOR
FIRST RESPONDER. IT'S THE EXACT SAME DRONE
TECHNOLOGY THAT THE POLICE DEPARTMENT CURRENTLY USES OUT
OF THE REAL TIME INVESTIGATION CENTER.
THIS ITEM IS ONE IN WHICH WE ARE GOING TO PARTNER WITH THE
POLICE DEPARTMENT, HAVE THAT INFORMATION AS A PART OF
ARCTIC. FOR US SPECIFICALLY THERE ARE
TWO THINGS ONE IN OUR AREAS OF RESPONSIBILITY HERE IN THE
CITY. ONE OF THEM IS THE DEPARTMENT
OF PUBLIC HEALTH GENERAL HOSPITAL AND ALL OF THE
SURROUNDING AREAS. WE HAVE TO DEAL WITH PEOPLE WHO
ARE WALKWAYS AGAINST MEDICAL ADVICE SOMETIMES PEOPLE WHO ARE
FOR BETTER LACK OF A BETTER TERM MISSING PERSONS.
THE DRONE WILL HELP US TO SEARCH FOR THOSE INDIVIDUALS
IN A MORE EFFICIENT, TIMELY MANNER ESPECIALLY WITH
INDIVIDUALS WHO HAVE MEDICAL CONDITIONS WHO MAY NEED
IMMEDIATE HELP AND ASSISTANCE. IN ADDITION, THOUGH, THE DRONE
ITSELF WILL ALSO BE A PART OF OUR TECHS DEPLOYMENT THROUGHOUT
OUR CITY. THE SECOND ITEM TO SUPERVISOR
WALTON IS WHAT IS CALLED A TEAR BALL GRENADE.
IT'S ACTUALLY A CANISTER WHICH HAS NOT TEAR GAS BUT OZONE
PEPPER SPRAY IN IT AND THIS IS TO ADDRESS WHAT HAPPENED A FEW
YEARS AGO WHEN WE HAD DISPENSERS CANISTERS THAT HAD
SEE US AND SEEN GAS. AND DURING A TRAINING EXERCISE
THAT GAS WAS DISPERSED AND UNFORTUNATELY WENT INTO A
PUBLIC AREA INTO A SCHOOL AND AFFECTED MEMBERS OF THE SAN
BRUNO COMMUNITY. THE TEAR BALL GRENADE IS
ACTUALLY A DEVICE WHICH IS INTENDED TO DELIVER OZONE
PEPPER SPRAY NOT SEEN OR SEE US GAS INTO A SPECIFIC AREA.
AND IT'S TO ADDRESS OUR SAFETY CONCERN REGARDING HAVING AN
INCREASE IN OUR POPULATION RIGHT NOW OUR INCARCERATED
POPULATION WHICH ARE HOUSED IN DORMITORY TYPE AREAS.
SO THEY'RE IN AREAS OUT AT SAN BRUNO.
IT WAS SOMETHING WHICH ONE UTILIZES A CHEMICAL AGENT THAT
WE ALREADY CARRY ON OUR TOOL BELT.
SO IT'S NOT SOMETHING NEW AND THE DELIVERY SYSTEM ITSELF
IS NOT INTEND IT TO INDIVIDUALIZE ON ANY SPECIFIC
PERSON. IT'S FOR DEPLOYMENT INTO AN
AREA. AND SO THE DELIVERY SYSTEM
ITSELF IS SOMETHING WE CURRENTLY HAVE WITH RCN AND SEE
US GASES. >> I MEAN JUST LAST QUESTION IS
THERE ANY WAY TO GUARANTEE THAT DRONE TECHNOLOGY WON'T VIOLATE
SOMEONE'S CIVIL RIGHTS LIKE PEOPLE EVEN UNINTENDED FOR
BEING CAPTURED ON CAMERA OR ETC.?
>> CURRENT POLICY THAT WE HAVE IS CONSISTENT WITH WHAT IS
BEING USED RIGHT NOW FOR ALL OF OUR DRONE DEPLOYMENTS IN THE
CITY WILL FALL UNDER THE SAME GUIDELINES, THE SAME CRITERIA.
WE DON'T HAVE ANY FACIAL RECOGNITION TECHNOLOGY ON IT OR
WE DON'T HAVE A DELIVERABLE SYSTEM.
WE'RE NOT INTENDING THIS TO BE ANYTHING THAT WE DELIVER THINGS
ON. IT'S STRICTLY INTENDED TO BE AN
OBSERVATION PLATFORM FOR US TO GIVE YOU AN IDEA OF WHAT ITS
VALUE IS TO US SPECIFICALLY AT THE SHERIFF'S OFFICE THE DIA
FOR IS GOING TO ONCE WE DEPLOY THIS THIS IS OUR ONLY OUR FIRST
ONE AND WE INTEND TO DEPLOY IT OUT AT SAN BRUNO, OUR LARGEST
FACILITY. WE HAVE AN INCREASED EXCUSE ME
IN INDIVIDUALS WHO ARE OUTSIDE IN OUR YARDS IN OUR OUTSIDE
AREAS. THIS ACTUALLY HELPS US TO
SUPPLEMENT OUR STAFFING SO THAT INSTEAD OF HAVING A DEPUTY THAT
HAS TO BE OUT THERE ON THE OUTER PERIMETER WE HAVE DRONES
THAT WILL BE ABLE TO MONITOR BEHAVIORS INSIDE OF THESE
OUTSIDE AREAS. SO THAT HELPS US TO REDUCE THE
NEED FOR STAFFING. THANK YOU, SHERIFF.
AND JUST TO NOTE, I DON'T THINK THERE IS ANY WAY POSSIBLE FOR
THERE'S ANY WAY POSSIBLE TO PROTECT EVERYONE'S CIVIL RIGHTS
WITH DRONE TECHNOLOGY. I MEAN JUST YOU CAN SEE
SOMETHING THAT SOMEBODY DOESN'T WANT YOU TO SEE THAT GETS
CAPTURED BY THAT DRONE. SO MY NO WON'T JUST BE APPLYING
THE YOU WOULD ALSO APPLIES TO THE POLICE DEPARTMENT.
>> THANK YOU. OKAY.
THANK YOU. PRESIDENT BENJAMIN.
SURE. AND THIS IS A ROLL CALL.
YES. YES.
THANK YOU. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL AND ITEM 20 SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR
WALTON NO WALTON. NO SUPERVISOR WONG WANG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN I CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN RIGHT MANDOLIN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYE THERE ARE EIGHT EYES
AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON THERE ARE NINE EYES
AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON VOTING NO AND THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM
22 AND 20 TWO? >> THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO
TEMPORARILY EXCLUDE CERTAIN SITES FROM THE PROVISION OF
CALIFORNIA SENATE BILL NUMBER 79 THAT REQUIRE LOCAL
JURISDICTIONS TO ALLOW RESIDENTIAL USES AT VARIOUS
DENSITIES HEIGHTS AND FLOOR AREA RATIOS ON SITES WITHIN ONE
HALF MILE OF A TRANSIT ORIENTED DEVELOPMENT STOP TO PERMANENTLY
EXCLUDE FROM THOSE PROVISIONS OF SB 79.
SITES LOCATED TWO INDUSTRIAL EMPLOYMENT HUBS INCLUDING
CERTAIN ZONE SITES AND SITES WITH A WALKING PATH OF MORE
THAN ONE MILE TO THE CLOSEST TO TRANSIT DEVELOPMENT STOP TO
AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO PERMIT ADDITIONAL DENSITY
AND HEIGHT FOR RESIDENTIAL PROJECTS ON CERTAIN PARCELS
WITHIN ONE HALF MILE OF A TRANSIT ORIENTED DEVELOPMENT.
STOP TO ADOPT AN ALTERNATIVE PLAN TO SB 79 TO INCLUDE MAKING
FINDINGS THAT THE ALTERNATIVE PLAN PROVIDE EQUIVALENT
DEVELOPMENT CAPACITY TO MAKE FINDINGS THAT THESE EXEMPTIONS
AND THE CITY'S RESIDENTIAL CAPACITY MEET THE REQUIREMENTS
OF SB 79 AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN COLLEAGUES AS SOME OF YOU KNOW I HAVE HAD
RESERVATIONS ABOUT THIS LEGISLATION IN MY TIME ON THIS
BOARD. I'VE BEEN CONSISTENT IN MY
STANCE ON HOUSING POLICY AND THAT I THINK WE NEED TO DO
EVERYTHING WE CAN TO ELIMINATE BARRIERS TO HOUSING PRODUCTION.
I ALSO THINK OUR HOUSING SHORTAGE IS TOO ACUTE FOR US TO
BE SAYING NO OR TO ALLOW TO BE ALLOWING THE PERFECT TO BE THE
ENEMY OF THE GOOD. SO I DO HAVE RESERVATIONS ABOUT
PURSUING AN ALTERNATIVE PLAN TO SB 79 AT ALL.
I THINK WE SHOULD BE USING EVERY TOOL WE HAVE TO INCREASE
OUR HOUSING CAPACITY AND THAT CAN BE ACCOMPLISHED THROUGH A
COMBINATION OF STATE MANDATES AND LOCAL ZONING AND FINANCIAL
STRUCTURES. HAVING SAID THAT, THERE IS A
PLAN IN FRONT OF US. AS I STATED WHEN I JOINED THE
LAND USE COMMITTEE DISCUSSION LAST WEEK, I HAVE CONCERNS WITH
PERMANENTLY EXEMPTING ANY AREAS I THOUGHT THE PERMANENT
EXEMPTION WAS TO DETERMINATIVE. AND AFTER A LOT OF THOUGHT I
LEFT THAT MEETING INTENDING TO VOTE NO ON THIS ITEM.
HOWEVER, IN THE LAST FEW DAYS I HAVE LEARNED THAT THE
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT HCD IS REVIEWING OUR DRAFT PLAN AND THAT THEY
HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT WHETHER WE CAN EXCLUDE PERSONAL PARCELS
IN MY DISTRICT THAT ARE CURRENTLY LISTED AS PERMANENTLY
EXEMPT. SO I'M VERY INTERESTED TO LEARN
MORE ABOUT THEIR INTERPRETATION AND I LOOK FORWARD TO RECEIVING
THEIR GUIDANCE. THAT DETERMINATION WON'T CHANGE
UNDERLYING ZONING BUT IT WILL PROVIDE US WITH HELPFUL
GUIDANCE ON HOW WE TREAT THESE AREAS IN FUTURE POLICY
DISCUSSIONS. THIS PROCESS I THINK HAS
HIGHLIGHTED GAPS IN OUR DISTRICT SIX ZONING POLICY THAT
I WILL BE EXPLORING SEPARATELY REGARDLESS OF CDW'S GUIDANCE.
I KNOW THAT THERE ARE THINGS MY COLLEAGUES LIKE ABOUT THIS PLAN
AND WHILE I MYSELF HAVE RESERVATIONS, THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT HAS SUGGESTED AN AMENDMENT AFFECTING MY DISTRICT
THAT I AM WILLING TO SUPPORT. IT PRESERVES THE PLAN
AND PROVIDES FOR FLEXIBILITY ON THIS.
EACH COULD DETERMINATION OECD'S GUIDANCE IS IN IS NOT IN OUR
HANDS BUT PERVERT BUT PRESERVING THE PLAN IS VERY
MUCH WITHIN OUR HANDS AND THIS AMENDMENT WOULD HELP US DO THAT
PLANNING CIRCULATED THE AMENDMENT EARLIER BUT I WOULD
LIKE IF THROUGH THE CHAIR TO OFFER THE DEPARTMENT AN
OPPORTUNITY IF I MIGHT JUST TO EXPLAIN THE DETAILS OF THE
AMENDMENT. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
>> THANK YOU. DORSEY CHAIR MANDOLIN PRESIDENT
MANDOLIN. >> I'M JOSHUA SAWICKI WITH
PLANNING STAFF AND I BELIEVE YOU HAVE THE AMENDMENT AS
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DESCRIBED IT IS AN UNCLASSIFIED PRIVATE NEW
SECTION AT THE END OF THE ORDINANCE WHICH BASICALLY
STATES THAT FOLLOWING THE ADOPTION OF THIS ORDINANCE BY
THE BOARD AND US FORWARDING IT TO TO THE STATE TO CD THAT IF
THEY DETERMINE THAT ANY OF THE PARCELS THAT THE BOARD'S
ORDINANCE HAS PUT FORWARD AS EXEMPT TURN OUT UNDER THEIR
DETERMINATION NOT TO BE ELIGIBLE FOR THAT THEN THE
PLANNING DIRECTOR CAN UPDATE THOSE TABLES ACCORDINGLY TO
REFLECT THE FINAL DETERMINATION BY EACH CITY AND THAT WE CAN DO
THAT ADMINISTRATIVELY WITHOUT COMING BACK TO THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AGAIN. THIS IS THIS WOULD PRESERVE THE
ALTERNATIVE PLAN INTACT. >> THIS IS CLEARLY A VERY
NUANCED AND CONFUSING STATE LAW.
>> BUT BECAUSE WE ARE PUTTING FORWARD AN ALTERNATIVE PLAN
THAT COVERS THE ENTIRE CITY, IT WOULD EXEMPT THE ENTIRE CITY
EFFECTIVELY FROM THE IMPLEMENTATION OF SB 79 BECAUSE
WE MEET THE REQUIREMENTS AND EVEN IF SOME PARCELS
IN THESE AREAS ARE DEEMED INELIGIBLE FOR THESE SPECIFIC
EXEMPTIONS, THAT DOESN'T NECESSARILY JEOPARDIZE OUR
ENTIRE ALTERNATIVE PLAN THAT COVERS THE ENTIRE CITY FOR THE
NEXT SIX YEARS. AND SO BY BY ADOPT BY APPROVING
THIS AMENDMENT WE COULD ADMINISTRATIVELY KEEP THE
ALTERNATIVE PLAN MOVING FORWARD ON ITS ON ITS SCHEDULE SO THAT
SO THAT YOU CAN CERTIFY IT BEFORE SB 79 TAKES EFFECT ON
JULY FIRST AND THE END RESULT WOULD BE THE SAME THAT NO
PARCEL IN THE CITY WOULD BE SUBJECT TO HAVING ITS ZONING
OVERRIDDEN BY SB 79 FOR THE NEXT SEVERAL YEARS.
>> SO HAPPY TO ANSWER ANY OTHER QUESTIONS.
GREAT. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. I SEE THAT THERE I HAVE SOME
COLLEAGUES ON THE ROSTER BUT I WILL ADD THAT WE ARE ADVISED BY
THE CITY ATTORNEY THAT THIS AMENDMENT IS NON SUBSTANTIVE.
SO I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO ADOPT THE AMENDMENT
THAT WAS DESCRIBED JUST DESCRIBED BY THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT AND I WILL READ THAT INTO THE RECORD JUST FOR
TRANSPARENCY THIS WOULD BE APPENDED TO THE END OF THE
ORDINANCE CREATING A SECTION TEN UPDATES TO TABLES OF
EXEMPTIONS IF ANY PARCEL IDENTIFIED IN THE TABLE OF
PERMANENT EXEMPTIONS REFERENCED IN SECTION THREE OR THE TABLE
OF TEMPORARY EXEMPTIONS LOW RESOURCE PARCELS REFERENCED
IN SECTION FOUR BECOMES INELIGIBLE FOR THE APPLICABLE
EXEMPTION FOR ANY REASON INCLUDING ADMINISTRATIVE
INTERPRETATION FROM EACH CD THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AUTHORIZES
THE DIRECTOR OF PLANNING TO UPDATE THESE TABLES TO REMOVE
THE INELIGIBLE PARTNER PART SALES SUCH THAT ONLY THE
REMAINING ELIGIBLE PARCELS ARE LISTED IN THE TABLE FOR THEIR
RELEVANT EXEMPTION. ANY CHANGES TO ADD PREVIOUSLY
UNIDENTIFIED PARCELS TO EITHER TABLE OR THAT WOULD RESULT
IN INCREASED DENSITY OR HEIGHTS FOR A PARCEL LISTED IN EITHER
TABLE SHALL REQUIRE APPROVAL FROM THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND THAT'S THE AMENDMENT. >> THERE'S BEEN A MOTION FROM
SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND A SECOND FROM SUPERVISOR MAHMUD AND WE
WILL CONTINUE WITH OUR DISCUSSION SUPERVISOR ON THANK
YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT IF WE COULD GET A REPRESENTATIVE FROM
PLANNING AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR BEING HERE BUT HOW WOULD
THIS AMENDMENT ALTER ACT THE AUTHORITY OVER SAN FRANCISCO
LIKE SOME OTHER WORDS DOES THIS GIVE THEM MORE POWER TO MAKE A
BRING YOU KNOW, MAKE A DECISION OVER US?
>> THE ANSWER IS NO. IT DOES NOT GIVE CITY ANY MORE
AUTHORITY THAN THEY ALREADY HAVE.
THEY MAKE THE FINAL DETERMINATION AND ON THE
INTERPRETATION OF THE LAW WE PUT FORWARD WHAT WE THINK
COMPLIES. >> IF THEY DETERMINE THAT IT'S
INELIGIBLE, IT'S NOT HAS NOTHING TO DO WITH THIS
AMENDMENT OR OR NOT THIS AMENDMENT AND DOES IT CHANGE
ZONING CONTROLS THAT APPLY TO ANY PARCEL AND SAN FRANCISCO NO
IT WOULDN'T AND WE ARE CONFIDENT THAT THE ALTERNATIVE
PLAN WILL STILL STAND EVEN IF SOME OF THESE PARCELS ARE
DEEMED INELIGIBLE AND AS A RESULT OF HAVING THE
ALTERNATIVE PLAN IN PLACE THE RESULT WOULD BE THAT NO PARCELS
WOULD BE AFFECTED BEYOND WHAT WE'VE ALREADY PROVIDED TO THE
TO THE BOARD. >> AND JUST A GUESS WHAT IS
CONCERNING LIKE WHY DID WE DECIDE TO DO THIS IN THE 11TH
HOUR BECAUSE WE'VE BEEN HAVING THESE CONVERSATIONS FOR A WHILE
. IT'S JUST AS AS THIS ORDINANCE
HAS BEEN WORKING ITS WAY THROUGH THERE HAVE BEEN, YOU
KNOW, ONGOING NEW ISSUES WITH EACH CITY, NEW INTERPRETATIONS
THAT HAVE MADE IT CLEAR THAT THERE'S YOU KNOW, THERE'S SOME
CONTINUING SOME ONGOING LACK OF CLARITY WITH HPD ON ON SOME YOU
YOU KNOW, PROVISIONS OF SB 79 AND SO THE CITY ATTORNEY EVEN
RECOMMENDED THAT WE PUT THIS IN HERE TO PRESERVE OUR
SCHEDULES SO THAT WE CAN KEEP MOVING FORWARD ON THE ON THE
PATH TO GETTING OUR ALTERNATIVE PLAN CERTIFIED BEFORE THE
DEADLINE. >> AND YOU HAVE SOME IF I MAY I
JUST WANTED TO COMMENT SORRY. LISA GLUCKSTEIN PLANNING
DEPARTMENT STAFF AS WELL. I JUST WANT TO COMMENT THAT CD
IS STILL VERY MUCH IN THE PROCESS OF INTERPRETING THE
STATUTE WHICH IS, YOU KNOW, FRUSTRATING ON OUR END WHERE
WHILE WE'RE TRYING TO DEVELOP A PLAN BUT THEY WERE RECEIVING
LIVE GUIDANCE AND THESE ONGOING CALLS THAT WE HAVE WITH THEM
AND SO WE WANT TO BUILD INTO THE PURPOSE OF THIS AMENDMENT
IS TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT SOME OF THEIR INTERPRETATIONS CAN
CHANGE AND WE WANT TO BE PREPARED TO RESPOND QUICKLY SO
THAT WE CAN PRESERVE OUR ALTERNATIVE PLAN IN RESPONSE TO
ANY INTERPRETATIONS THAT GET FINALIZED AFTER WE ADOPT THIS
ORDINANCE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MADAM CHAIR MUGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT
MANDOLIN AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND STAFF
AND THE LADIES IN TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE
HEARD THIS ITEM AND CONSIDER IT AN AMENDMENT BY SUPERVISOR
DORSEY AT WHICH WOULD HAVE MADE THE PERMANENT RESTRICTION OF A
BUILDING HOUSING AND INDUSTRIAL PARCELS AND SALLY AND PDR
TEMPORARY SORT OF THING. >> NOTHING WOULD HAVE CHANGED
IN THEM DOES IT WOULD HAVE SIGNALED THAT WE WERE GOING TO
CONSIDER THEM BECAUSE THAT'S WHAT'S AT ISSUE HERE LOOKING AT
WHETHER OR NOT THIS YOU KNOW, WOULD MAKE US COMPLY WITH SB 70
NINE AT THE END THE AT THE LAND USE COMMITTEE ACT DID NOT
APPROVE THAT AMENDMENT THAT WAS PUT FORWARD BY ONE OF OUR
COMMITTEE MEMBERS, SUPERVISOR MAHMUD BECAUSE THAT'S NOT
USUALLY THE WAY WE DO THINGS IN SAN FRANCISCO THE PERMANENT
RESTRICTIONS AND DEATH DRILL PARCELS WERE DONE OVER THE
YEARS IN A COLLABORATIVE EFFORT WITH THE COMMUNITY TO TO
PRESERVE NOT JUST HOUSING BECAUSE HOUSING IS SUPER
IMPORTANT BUT ALSO BLUE COLLAR INDUSTRIAL JOBS WHICH ARE ALSO
VERY IMPORTANT. IT IS SORT OF THE BACKBONE OF
WORKING CLASS COMMUNITIES PEOPLE WHO DON'T HAVE COLLEGE
DEGREES THAT STILL HAVE ACCESS TO HAVING WELL-PAYING JOBS
IN OUR CITY AND SO, YOU KNOW, I DO GENERALLY THINK THAT HAVING
PERMANENT ANYTHING IS NOT A GOOD IDEA AND PLANNING BECAUSE
THINGS CHANGE BUT YOU DO IT THOUGHTFULLY.
YOU KNOW, WE I JUST WANT TO YOU KNOW, JUST RELATE AS BACK TO
WHAT WE JUST WENT THROUGH WITH THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN.
WE ALL GOT IN THERE ROLLED UP OUR SLEEVES.
NONE OF US GOT EVERYTHING WE WANTED BUT IT TOOK US A LONG
TIME TO GET THROUGH IT BECAUSE WE NEGOTIATED WITH COMMUNITY.
WE MADE THE INFORMATION TRANSPARENT.
>> ALL OF THESE THINGS HAPPENED RIGHT?
THAT'S THE WAY WE IN A CITY AS DIVERSE SHARING THESE LIKE
SEVEN BY SEVEN SQUARE MILES USUALLY MAKE DECISIONS ABOUT
PLANNING FOR THE LAND AND HOW WE USE IT.
SO DURING THOSE CONVERSATIONS WE AT THE LAND USE COMMITTEE
SAID TO COMMUNITY WHO ARE VERY WORRIED ABOUT SB 79 DON'T
WORRY. WE ALSO ARE PLANNING TO BE
EXEMPTED FROM SB 79 BY DOING THESE THINGS AND GET THAT MAP
ABOUT THE PARCELS THAT WERE AFFECTED BY SB 79 WERE PUT OUT
TO THE COMMUNITY DURING THE PROCESS OF THE FAMILY ZONING
PLAN I MADE. >> MR. LEWICKI HURRY UP AND GET
THAT DONE EVEN THOUGH IT WAS A LITTLE BIT STRESSFUL BECAUSE WE
WANTED COMMUNITY TO UNDERSTAND ALL OF THESE THINGS.
SO NONE OF THIS IS NEW. >> WHAT IS NEW IS THIS LAST
MINUTE SORT OF ISSUE WITH EACH CITY ABOUT THE INDUSTRIAL
AREAS. I THINK THAT THE PLAN THAT
WE'VE COME UP WITH TO JUST TAKE THEM OUT OF THE CALCULATION IS
FINE. IT DOESN'T CHANGE THE ZONING AS
SUPERVISOR WALTON DOES. IT DOESN'T DO ANYTHING.
WE GOT A LETTER FROM SOME OF THE ADVOCATES SAYING THIS IS
GOING TO LEAD TO SPECULATIVE YOU KNOW, BUYING UP OF THESE
PARCELS. I DON'T BELIEVE THAT'S WHAT'S
GOING TO HAPPEN. I DON'T THINK ANYBODY'S GOING
TO PLOP DOWN A BUNCH OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS FOR A PIECE
OF LAND NOT REALLY KNOWING WHAT IT'S WORTH OR WHAT CAN BE DONE
ON IT. SO ALL YOU KNOW, I WILL SUPPORT
THE AMENDMENT BUT I DO SO RELUCTANT BECAUSE I DON'T THINK
THIS THERE'S ANY HURRY HERE. I REALLY DON'T.
I THINK WE COULD HAVE WAITED A WEEK OR TWO TO GET CLARITY FROM
A CD. THERE HAS NOT BEEN A
DETERMINATION FROM A CD THAT HAS NOT YET HAPPENED.
I WISH IT HAD BECAUSE YOU KNOW IT WOULD JUST GUIDE US BETTER.
I DO UNDERSTAND THAT ALL YOU KNOW, LAND USE ISSUES ARE
CONTENTIOUS IN OUR CITY. I THINK THAT WE DON'T WANT TO
RISK THE ENTIRETY OF THE EXEMPTION OFF OF SB 79 FOR THE
WEST SIDE FOR THE EAST SIDE, FOR ALL OF US.
YOU KNOW, BASED ON A FEW PARCELS WHEN WE KNOW THAT
NOTHING'S GOING TO HAPPEN TO IT .
SO THAT'S WHY I'M SUPPORTING YOUR AMENDMENT.
BUT I JUST WANT TO SAY TO PLANNING THERE'S NO REASON TO
FREAK OUT THE COMMUNITY AND TO, YOU KNOW, ERODE THE TRUST THAT
YOU'VE WORKED SO HARD TO BUILD WITH FOLKS IN THE COMMUNITY.
>> THERE'S NO REASON FOR IT BECAUSE THERE'S NO HURRY.
I THINK WE COULD HAVE WAITED A WEEK OR TWO TO GET CLARITY
AND GET THIS DONE. I UNDERSTAND THAT THIS WAS ON
THE DOCKET. YOU KNOW, I'M JUST SAYING NEXT
TIME YOU KNOW, PERHAPS THE CHAIR OF THE CITRUS RIDGE
COMMITTEE WILL BE MORE JUDICIOUS AND WHEN WE SCHEDULE
THINGS, YOU KNOW, JUST TO GIVE PEOPLE TIME BECAUSE I DO THINK
THAT THAT'S ALSO IMPORTANT TO THE PROCESS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, CHAIR MAJOR
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD COLLEAGUES JUST WANTED TO SHARE WHY A
SECOND THE MOTION FROM SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND ALSO WHY
I ORIGINALLY PUT FORTH THE AMENDMENT PROPOSAL BY
SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR A VOTE IN THE PLANNING IN THE LAND USE
COMMITTEE IN COMMITTEE I INTRODUCED THAT AMENDMENT TO
SHORTEN THE TIMELINE UNDER WHICH SB 79 RULES WOULD NOT
APPLY TO CERTAIN INDUSTRIAL EMPLOYMENT HUBS.
I DID SO BECAUSE I FELT THAT IT WOULD ENCOURAGE MORE FRANK
CONVERSATION ABOUT THE FUTURE OF THESE ZONES PARTICULARLY
WHEN THEY ALREADY ALLOW HOUSING BECAUSE WE NEED THE OPTIONALITY
SHOULD WE NEED TO IN 2029 WHEN WE MAYBE DON'T MEET OUR HOUSING
GOALS OR THE HOUSING ELEMENT AND MAYBE TRIGGER A CIRCUIT
BREAKER THE OPTIONALITY TO POTENTIALLY BUILD HOUSING THERE
AND POTENTIAL AREAS THAT WERE ALREADY PROVISIONED WOULD HAVE
BEEN HELPFUL AND IT WOULD HAVE BEEN A TEMPORARY EXEMPTION TO
SB 79. WE OBVIOUSLY HEARD FROM
COMMUNITY MEMBERS AT COMMITTEE ON MULTIPLE SIDES BUT INCLUDING
THOSE THAT SAID THAT THOSE HUBS AND SOMA ARE ALREADY MIXED USE
IN NATURE AND THERE'S A DESIRE FOR MORE HOUSING TO BE BUILT
IN THOSE AREAS. THE AMENDMENT DID NOT PASS AS
WAS NOTED AND I DON'T INTEND TO INTRODUCE IT AGAIN HERE AS
SUPERVISOR DORSEY MENTIONED. BUT I HOPE THAT THE
CONVERSATION CONTINUES ABOUT ALLOWING HOUSING AND MIXED USE
AREAS IN SOMA AND I TRUST SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT ARE GOING TO CONTINUE THAT.
I ALSO NOTE THAT WE DID CALL INTO QUESTION AT THAT COMMITTEE
HEARING WHETHER WE WERE EVEN ALLOWED TO PERMANENTLY EXEMPT
ZONES WHERE HOUSING WAS ALLOWED UNDER SB 79.
UNDER THIS LEGISLATION AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS
CONDITIONALLY ALLOWED IN THE SERVICE ARTS AND LIGHT
INDUSTRIAL ZONE IN SOMA WHICH IS EXCLUDED UNDER THIS PLAN.
WE WERE TOLD IN COMMITTEE AT THE TIME THAT THE CITY WAS
CONFIDENT IN THEIR INTERPRETATION BUT WE ARE
HEARING THIS AMENDMENT NOW TODAY BECAUSE IT IS CLEAR THAT
SUBSEQUENT CONVERSATIONS WITH THE HOUSING COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT DEPARTMENT MADE IT CLEAR THAT THERE IS STILL SOME
WORK TO DO AND UNDERSTANDING WHAT WE CAN AND CANNOT LEGALLY
EXCLUDE FROM OUR POSITIONING AND OUR OUR SB 79 ALTERNATIVE
PLAN. SO I'M THANKFUL FOR THIS
AMENDMENT THAT WILL ALLOW THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO MAKE
NECESSARY CHANGES TO COMPLY WITH IT AND ENSURE THAT OUR
HOUSING ELEMENT IS IN COMPLIANCE AND THAT IS WHY I
INTEND TO VOTE FOR THIS AMENDMENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. THERE'S NO ONE ELSE ON THE
ROSTER. SUPERVISOR DORSEY HAS MADE A
MOTION TO AMEND IT HAS BEEN SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR MAHMUD
BY THE TENOR OF THE CONVERSATION.
>> THAT SOUNDS LIKE WE CAN TAKE THAT MOTION WITHOUT OBJECTION.
>> OH, NOPE. WE'RE GOING TO A ROLL CALL.
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE ON THE MOTION ON THE MOTION TO
ITEM 22. >> SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN EYE MENDELSON EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR EYE AND SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYE
THERE ARE NINE EYES AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR CHAN VOTING NO
THE MOTION IS APPROVED. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN TANGO
PRESIDENT MADAM AND I FIRST WANT TO THANK OUR CHAIRMAN GA
FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP ON CLEARLY ON THE NOT ONLY THE FAMILY
ZONING PLAN BUT NOW THAT TACKLING THE SB 79 WE HAVE A
LONG DISCUSSION ABOUT SB 79 FRANKLY AND THAT YOU KNOW WE
HAD OR I SHOULD SAY I HAVE PROPOSED A RESOLUTION OPPOSING
THE SB 79 WITH THE UNDERSTANDING AND THE CONCERN
FRANKLY IS THAT WHILE IN SUPPORT OF HAVING BUILDING
HOUSING ALONG THE TRANSIT ORIENTED CORRIDOR, THE CONCERN
HAS ALWAYS BEEN THE PROTECTION FOR RESIDENTS, TENANTS
AND SMALL BUSINESS. I THINK I THINK WHAT HAS BEEN
HAPPENING SINCE THE PASSAGE OF FAMILY ZONING PLAN TO DATE
AND WHAT IT'S BEFORE US TODAY AND THEN CONTINUING THE
AMENDMENT WITH SUPERVISOR DORSEY IT SEEMS LIKE I AM I AM
I AM STILL WHERE I WAS AND WHERE I'VE BEEN THAT AS YOU
CONTINUE TO EVOLVE IT BECOMES A MOCKERY.
>> IT SEEMS LIKE IT'S BECOMING A MOCKERY OF ALL OF US OF ALL
THE TIME AND EFFORTS THAT WE HAVE SPENT AND TO PROVIDE
FURTHER EXEMPTION IN THE AREA WHERE IN MY OPINION SHOULD BE
ALSO INCLUSIVE IN OTHER AREAS THROUGHOUT THE CITY.
SO I WILL BE SUPPORTIVE OF THOSE I VOTED AGAINST THEM
AND IS NOT BECAUSE THAT I THINK I JUST THINK THAT BY NOW THE
SENTIMENT I VOTE I VOTED NOT AGAINST LANGUAGE BUT THE
SENTIMENT THE SENTIMENTS ITSELF THAT SOMEHOW WE AGAIN YOU KNOW
THAT ALLOWING A STATE GOVERNMENT TO HAVE SUCH A
MICROMANAGEMENT OF OUR LAND USE PLANNING AND AND DECISION
MAKING PROCESS COMPLETELY TAKE AWAY EVEN WITH THE THREATS OF
BUILDERS RAMADI BUT THEN ACTUALLY THROUGHOUT THIS
PROCESS HAVE CLEARLY SHOWN US ALL OF US AND SAN FRANCISCANS
THAT THE STATE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN OVERREACH IN THE WAY THAT
DICTATING OUR LOCAL GOVERNMENT HAVING PLANNING AND AND ZONING
ISSUES AND AND OUR ZONING POLICIES.
>> SO IT'S ONLY THE REASON WHY I VOTED AGAINST THAT.
>> BUT I WILL BE VOTING IN SUPPORT OF IT BECAUSE THEN
AGAIN WITH THE CONSIDERATION THAT YOU KNOW, DEFERENTIAL TO
MY COLLEAGUES, PARTICULARLY SUPERVISOR WALTON AND ALSO
SUPPLIES OF FILTER THAT AGAIN THESE ARE IMPACTFUL TO THE
PROSPECTIVE DISTRICTS THAT I TRULY BELIEVE IN NEEDS
PROTECTION BUT I DO NOT THINK I DO NOT THINK THAT IT ACTUALLY
SOLVE NEITHER THE HOUSING CRISIS OR TO PROTECTION FOR
TENANTS AND SMALL BUSINESS ISSUES THAT SAN FRANCISCO FACE
. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE AMENDED ITEM ON ITEM 20 TWO AS AMENDED
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SARDAR
SARDAR I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE AMENDED
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO
OUR 2:30 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER YES THE 2:30 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER IS
THE RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS
SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND TODAY WE
ARE STARTING WITH DISTRICT THREE SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK
YOU PRESIDENT MENTION TODAY I HAVE THE HONOR OF WELCOMING
SUSAN GAGE TO OUR CHAMBERS TO RECOGNIZE HER CONTRIBUTIONS TO
RUSSIAN HILL IN ALL OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SUSAN PLEASE COME ON UP AND JOIN US.
>> SAN FRANCISCO'S NEIGHBORHOODS ARE SPECIAL
BECAUSE OF THE PEOPLE THAT CARE FOR THEM AND MOVE THEM FORWARD.
SUSAN EMBODIES THIS AND I CONSIDER HER TO BE ONE OF THE
UNSUNG HEROES OF DISTRICT THREE.
IT IS NEARLY IMPOSSIBLE TO WALK AROUND RUSSIAN HILL AND NOT
BUMP INTO SUSAN USUALLY HARD AT WORK IN ONE OF HER MANY MANY
ENDEAVORS ON ANY GIVEN SATURDAY YOU'RE LIKELY TO FIND SUSAN AT
THE CORNER OF FILBERT AND HYDE TO KICK OFF THE CLEANUP
AND SMILE EVENT WHERE DOZENS OF VOLUNTEERS GATHER TO SPREAD OUT
ACROSS RUSSIAN HILL WITH TRASH BAGS AND PICKERS TO MAKE OUR
STREETS AND SIDEWALKS SHINE DURING HOLIDAYS YOU'LL FIND
SUSAN LEADING CELEBRATIONS FOR RUSSIAN HILL NEIGHBORS PUTTING
TO USE HER BACKGROUND IN CATERING AND ORGANIZING OF
LARGE EVENTS. IF YOU WERE EVER INVITED TO A
RUSSIAN HILL NEIGHBORS PARTY BE SURE TO GO BECAUSE YOU WILL
LEAVE HAPPY AND WELL-FED. AND JUST THIS PAST WEEKEND
SUSAN WAS COORDINATING FRANCISCO PARK'S FOURTH
ANNIVERSARY ALONGSIDE HER HUSBAND TOM.
THEY ORGANIZED YOGA KIDS ACTIVITIES AND A CAKE PICNIC
WITH DOZENS OF BEAUTIFULLY DECORATED CAKES.
I KNOW I WAS THERE AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL WAS THERE
AND AMIDST HUNDREDS OF PEOPLE IN LINE CLAMORING FOR CAKES,
SUSAN WAS CALMLY KEEPING EVERYONE IN LINE AND KEEPING
THINGS RUNNING. SHE WAS INSTRUMENTAL
IN SECURING THE EXPANSION OF MECHANICAL STREETS WEAVING
IN RUSSIAN HILL A SERVICE THAT ASTONISHINGLY MOST OF DISTRICT
THREE LACKS AND ALONGSIDE BARBARA BELLA SHE WAS MY
COUNTERPART AND HATCHING UP A NEW ANNUAL TRADITION THE GREAT
NEIGHBORHOOD TRASH OFF WHICH PITS NORTH BEACH AND RUSSIAN
HILL AGAINST EACH OTHER IN THE PURSUIT OF CLEANER
NEIGHBORHOODS. SUSAN DOES ALL OF THIS WORK
IN HER QUIET, STEADY WAY SHE CARES FOR THE COMMUNITY
AND NEIGHBORHOOD IN COUNTLESS WAYS UNSEEN AND UNSAID.
WE ARE SO BLESSED AND SO LUCKY TO HAVE HER STEWARDSHIP FOR SAN
FRANCISCO. SUSAN, THANK YOU FOR ALL YOU DO
AND I WOULD INVITE YOU NOW TO SAY A FEW WORDS IF YOU'D LIKE.
>> THANK YOU. BUT FIRST SUPERVISOR SHERYL
WOULD LIKE TO SAY SOME THINGS. >> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT
MANDOLIN AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER. I DON'T KNOW WHETHER TO THANK
YOU OR NOT BECAUSE SUSAN YOU CAUSED A MASSIVE FIGHT IN MY
HOUSE ON SATURDAY BETWEEN MY CHILDREN WHO ARE ARGUING OVER
WHETHER THE COCONUT CAKE OR THE S'MORES CAKE WAS BETTER AND OF
COURSE THEY WERE BOTH WRONG BECAUSE THE ANSWER WAS BOTH.
>> BUT IN ALL SERIOUSNESS, SUPERVISOR SLAUGHTER, THANK YOU
FOR RECOGNIZING SOMEONE WHOSE KINDNESS AND THOUGHTFULNESS IS
MATCHED ONLY BY HER BENT FOR ACTION.
YOU DON'T SIT BACK, YOU LEAN IN AND ALWAYS WITH THAT
OMNIPRESENT SMILE. AND I THINK WE'D ALSO BE REMISS
IF WE DIDN'T ACKNOWLEDGE TOM THANK YOU AS WELL FOR BEING
HERE AND SUPPORTING SUSAN AND I WANT TO THANK YOU BOTH FOR
REALLY BEING QUICK ON THE DRAW ON SATURDAY IN A VERY SCARY
SITUATION BUT SUPERVISOR THANK YOU FOR RECOGNIZING SOMEONE WHO
IS JUST A PURE JOY. >> CONGRATULATIONS SUSAN THANK
YOU. >> NOW THE FLOOR IS YOURS SO MY
HUSBAND AND I HAVE SPENT THE LAST 40 FIVE YEARS LIVING
IN WASHINGTON DC WE BUILT CAREERS, RAISED HER TWO
CHILDREN AND MADE A WONDERFUL LIFE THERE.
>> BUT TO BE HONEST, A PIECE OF MY HEART HAS ALWAYS BEEN IN SAN
FRANCISCO SO WE FIRST LIVED HERE IN THE 70S WHEN MY HUSBAND
WAS DOING HIS MEDICAL TRAINING AT UCSF AND THAT IS WHEN I FELL
IN LOVE WITH THIS CITY THE LIGHTS, THE BAY, THE HILLS
AND THE AMAZING COMMUNITY. >> I MADE MYSELF A QUIET
PROMISE THAT SOMEDAY I'M COMING BACK WELL THAT SOMEDAY IS NOW.
>> RETIREMENT GAVE ME THE GIFT OF CHOICE AND I CHOSE SAN
FRANCISCO A CITY THAT I HAVE LOVED FOR A VERY LONG TIME
AND GETTING TO BUILD A COMMUNITY HERE ALL OVER AGAIN
THAT FEELS LIKE THE GREATEST GIFT OF ALL.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH
DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR WONG K M CAN THE LAW HIGH SCHOOL GIRLS
SOCCER TEAM COME UP? >> GOOD AFTERNOON COLLEAGUES.
TODAY I'M PROUD TO RECOGNIZE THE LAW HIGH SCHOOL GIRLS
VARSITY SOCCER TEAM FOR AN EXTRAORDINARY 20 2526 SEASON
AND THEIR HISTORIC CIF STATE CHAMPIONSHIP VICTORY THE FIRST
TITLE IN PROGRAM HISTORY. AS SOMEONE WHO GREW UP IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND UNDERSTANDS HOW MUCH PRIDE OUR COMMUNITIES TAKE
IN OUR PUBLIC SCHOOLS, THIS RECOGNITION FEELS ESPECIALLY
MEANINGFUL TO ME WHEN OUR STUDENTS SUCCEED ARE A WHOLE
CITY SUCCEEDS SEEING A PUBLIC SCHOOL TEAM FROM CERTAIN
SCHOOLS REACH THIS LEVEL OF EXCELLENCE IS SOMETHING WE
SHOULD ALL BE PROUD OF. >> THIS ACHIEVEMENT MEANS SO
MUCH NOT ONLY TO THE PLAYERS BUT TO THE ENTIRE LOCAL
COMMUNITY. >> IT REFLECTS THE HARD WORK OF
STUDENTS, COACHES, TEACHERS, FAMILIES AND EVERYONE WHO
SUPPORTS THESE YOUNG ATHLETES BEHIND THE SCENES THIS SEASON
THE TEAM FINISHED WITH AN OUTSTANDING 15 TWO ZERO OVERALL
RECORD INCLUDING AN UNDEFEATED LEAGUE SEASON WITH 12 WINS
AND SECURED THEIR 29TH ACADEMIC ATHLETIC ASSOCIATION OR AA SAN
FRANCISCO SECTION CHAMPIONSHIP UP THEIR REMARKABLE POSTSEASON
RUN ESTABLISHED LAW AS ONE OF THE TOP HIGH SCHOOL SOCCER
PROGRAMS IN CALIFORNIA. >> NOW RANKED SIXTH IN THIS
STATE AND 36TH NATIONALLY. THIS KIND OF SUCCESS DOES NOT
HAPPEN BY ACCIDENT. IT COMES FROM DISCIPLINE,
TRUST, TEAMWORK AND SHOWING UP FOR ONE ANOTHER EVERY SINGLE
DAY. I WANT TO RECOGNIZE HEAD COACH
CHERYL FONG WHO'S HERE WITH US TODAY AND FOR BUILDING A
CHAMPION OWNERSHIP CALIBER PROGRAM AND CREATING A CULTURE
WHERE STUDENTS CAN THRIVE BOTH ON AND OFF THE FIELD.
I'D LIKE TO ESPECIALLY HIGHLIGHT TEAM CAPTAINS INCLUDE
DOG MATENGA OR MICK INTER AND KHALILAH SPURN FOR THEIR
EXCELLENCE IN LEADERSHIP AND SPORTSMANSHIP ALONG WITH
THEIR TEAMMATES THEY HAVE REPRESENTED LAW WITH PRIDE,
HUMILITY AND DETERMINATION. I KNOW WE ALSO HAVE SOME VERY
PROUD PARENTS AND FAMILY MEMBERS HERE TODAY AND I WANT
TO RECOGNIZE YOU AS WELL. BEHIND EVERY STUDENT ATHLETE IS
A STRONG SUPPORT SYSTEM. EARLY MORNINGS, LATE NIGHTS
RAISED TO PRACTICE AND CONSTANT ENCOURAGEMENT.
YOUR SACRIFICES OFTEN HAPPEN QUIETLY BUT THEY MATTER DEEPLY.
AND THIS ACHIEVEMENT BELONGS TO YOU TOO.
BEYOND ATHLETE ATHLETICS, THESE STUDENT ATHLETES ARE COMMITTED
TO ACADEMIC EXCELLENCE AND COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT.
THEY SERVE AS ROLE MODELS ACROSS CAMPUS AND FOR SAN
FRANCISCO AND THEIR HISTORIC SEASON HAS BROUGHT TREMENDOUS
PRIDE TO OUR CITY. WITH THAT I'D LIKE TO TURN IT
OVER TO PRINCIPAL BATISTE, JOAN BATISTE IS THE 22ND PRINCIPAL
OF LAW HIGH SCHOOL AND THE FOURTH ALUMNA TO LEAVE THE
INSTITUTE LEAD THE INSTITUTION A DEDICATED EDUCATOR WITH OVER
A DECADE OF EXPERIENCE IN THE S.F. USD.
SHE PREVIOUSLY SERVED AS LOWELL'S ASSISTANT PRINCIPAL OF
CURRICULUM AND INSTRUCTION AND IS A STRONG ADVOCATE FOR
STUDENT SUCCESS AND EDUCATIONAL EXCELLENCE.
>> JEN THANK YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP, YOUR DEDICATION TO
ALL STUDENTS AND YOUR CONTINUED COMMITMENT TO ACADEMIC
EXCELLENCE AND STUDENT SUCCESS. WE'RE GRATEFUL FOR ALL THAT YOU
DO FOR THE SCHOOL COMMUNITY AND HELPING SHAPE THE NEXT
GENERATION OF LEADERS. >> PRINCIPAL BATISTE BUT FIRST
HOLD ON. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU
SO MUCH. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WONG FOR THIS REALLY WONDERFUL
RECOGNITION. SO I AM SO PROUD OF THESE
LADIES. YOU ARE AWESOME.
YOU IT. I AM ALSO A LOW A HIGH SCHOOL
PARENT SO AS A PARENT I'M ALSO REALLY PROUD OF YOU.
IN ADDITION TO THE DISTRICT SEVEN SUPERVISOR.
WE HAVE A DISTRICT SEVEN YOUTH COUNCIL MANY OF YOU KNOW SOME
OF YOU HAVE YOUTH COUNCILS UP YOUR OWN NOW.
ONE OF THE RECOMMENDATIONS THAT THEY MADE THIS YEAR BECAUSE
THEY TELL ME WHAT TO DO IS THAT WE NEED TO RECOGNIZE WOMEN
SPORTS MORE. WE HAVE HAD COUNTLESS IN THIS
CHAMBER. WE HAVE HAD COUNTLESS
RECOGNITION OF BOYS TEAMS THAT HAVE DONE CHAMPIONSHIPS
AND WE'RE VERY PROUD OF THEM. BUT IT IS VERY SELDOM THAT WE
RECOGNIZE WOMEN'S SPORTS AND WE NEED TO DO MORE OF IT.
SO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WONG FOR RECOGNIZING THE VICTORY
THAT THESE LADIES HAD THE HARD WORK THAT WE'RE WENT INTO WITH
THE LEADERSHIP OF THE SCHOOL AND THE PARENTS IN BEING ABLE
TO SUPPORT THEIR SUCCESS. AND WE NEED TO BE JOYFUL ABOUT
IT, CELEBRATE IT MORE AND TO SEE YOU WE SEE YOU AND WE HONOR
YOU. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> AND NOW PRINCIPAL BATISTE, THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MENDELSOHN.
GOOD AFTERNOON. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
SUPERVISOR SUPERVISOR MELGAR AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
FOR WELCOMING OUR GIRLS SOCCER TEAM HERE.
THIS IS DEFINITELY A FIRST FOR ME AND FOR FOR US AS A DIVISION
OR AS A GROUP AS SUPERVISOR LONG SHARED OUR GIRLS VARSITY
SOCCER TEAM LED THE CITY BOTH GETTING THEIR TRIPLE-A
CHAMPIONSHIP IN AN UNDEFEATED LEAGUE AND ALSO WITH TWO LOSSES
IN OUTSIDE OF LEAGUE GAMES. >> AND THEY SECURED THE
DIVISION FIVE CIF STATE CHAMPIONSHIP.
THEY WERE THE FIRST EVER WOMEN'S HIGH SCHOOL SOCCER TEAM
IN THE HISTORY OF CALIFORNIA. >> AND THIS CHAMPIONSHIP COULD
NOT HAVE BEEN WITHOUT THE SUPPORT OF OUR COACHING STAFF
HAD SHOW HEAD COACH OUR COACH CHERYL FONG AND TORI PALMER
AND EUGENE VRANA. >> IT IS A GREAT JOB THAT THEY
HAVE DONE NOT JUST WITH THIS TEAM BUT OVER SEVERAL YEARS OF
WORK AND DEDICATION TO OUR STUDENTS.
THESE YOUNG WOMEN ARE BOTH ATHLETES AND THEY ARE ALSO
STUDENTS AND IF YOU HEAR FROM OUR STUDENTS THE HOURS OF
HOMEWORK THAT THEY DO ON TOP OF SHOWING UP WITH FULL OF ENERGY
READY TO PRACTICE AND TAKE ON THE FIELD IS SOMETHING THAT OUR
LAW STUDENTS DO DAY IN AND DAY OUT.
>> I ALSO WANT TO CELEBRATE OUR FAMILIES.
>> MY MOM WAS A SOCCER MOM OR MORE LIKE VOLLEYBALL
AND BASKETBALL MOM AND ALL OF THE GAMES.
THE TRAVEL THAT YOU ALL DID COMING OUT TO SACRAMENTO FOR
THE STATE CHAMPIONSHIP, GOING TO ALL OF THE DIFFERENT EVENTS
THAT THE STUDENTS HAD. THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR YOUR
TIME, DEDICATION AND SUPPORT FOR YOUR CHILDREN AND ALSO THE
LAW STAFF AND TEAM ARE ATHLETIC DIRECTORS.
CHRISSY HAS SOTA AND RAYMOND CHAN FOR PROVIDING THE
ENVIRONMENT WHERE THIS KIND OF EXCELLENCE CAN FLOURISH.
LOWELL HIGH SCHOOL HAS OVER 31 SPORTS TEAMS AND IT TAKES THOSE
TWO FOLKS AND THE SUPPORTIVE ADMINISTRATION AND THE COACHES
TO KEEP ALL OF THOSE TEAMS FUNCTIONING AND BEING ABLE TO
CELEBRATE THE SUCCESSES THAT THEY HAVE AND THE PLAYERS LED
BY CLAUDIA MCINTYRE AND KALEIL ASPEN YOU ARE THE EMBODIMENT OF
THE CARDINAL SPIRIT. YOU CELEBRATE THE COMMUNITY,
YOU HELP EACH OTHER OUT ACTING WITH INTEGRITY, TAKING THE
RISKS TO TAKE THE SHOTS OR CREATE SPACE FOR YOUR TEAMMATES
TO MAKE THOSE SHOTS AND BEING PATIENT WITH EACH OTHER AS YOU
ALL CONTINUE TO LEARN AND GROW WHETHER YOU ARE NAMED OUR CITY
PLAYER OF THE YEAR OR WERE THE TEAMMATE CHEERING THE LOUDEST
FROM THE SIDELINES, YOU PROVED THAT WHEN YOU COMBINE TALENT
AND DISCIPLINE YOU BECOME UNSTOPPABLE.
YOU HAVE BROUGHT TREMENDOUS PRIDE TO LOWELL AND THE ENTIRE
CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND I HOPE THAT YOU CONTINUE TO SET
THE NEW STANDARD FOR WHAT IT MEANS TO BE A STUDENT ATHLETE.
CONGRATULATIONS ON AN UNFORGETTABLE RECORD MAKING
SEASON. >> LET'S KEEP THAT MOMENTUM
GOING. OUTSIDE OF THE I MEAN THERE
WILL BE MORE PHOTOGRAPHS IN THE ROTUNDA.
>> NEXT UP DISTRICT FIVE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
>> COLLEAGUES IN HONOR TODAY OF AUTISM ACCEPTANCE MONTH.
I'M PROUD TO RECOGNIZE MIKA KIYA WISEMAN.
>> CAN YOU PLEASE COME UP TO THE PODIUM?
>> MIKA'S A NONPROFIT LEADER WHO IS DEDICATED ADVOCATE FOR
SAN FRANCISCO'S DISABILITY COMMUNITY.
THIS RECOGNITION IS ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL FOR ME BOTH
PERSONALLY AND IN WHAT IT REPRESENTS FOR OUR CITY BECAUSE
IT SPEAKS TO THE IMPORTANCE OF BUILDING A SAN FRANCISCO THAT
CENTERS UNDERSTANDING AND LIVED EXPERIENCE IN SHAPING PUBLIC
POLICY AND COMMUNITY LIFE. >> MIKA SERVES AS CO-DIRECTOR
OF THE SAN FRANCISCO DISABILITY CULTURAL CENTER, THE FIRST
PUBLICLY FUNDED DISABILITY CULTURAL CENTER IN THE ENTIRE
COUNTRY. >> IN THIS ROLE THEY HELP LEAD
A SPACE GROUNDED IN ACCESS AND CULTURAL CHANGE WHERE
DISABLED PEOPLE CAN ORGANIZE AND BUILD COMMUNITY ON THEIR
OWN TERMS. >> THE DISABILITY CULTURAL
CENTER OFFERS PROGRAMING DESIGNED TO REDUCE ISOLATION
AND FOSTER CONNECTION. ONE EXAMPLE IS TOGETHER TIME AN
OPEN VIRTUAL GATHERING WHERE COMMUNITY MEMBERS CAN SOCIALIZE
AND BUILD RELATIONSHIPS. MIKA HAS HELPED CREATE SUCH
SPACES FOR EMOTIONAL EXPRESSION AND SUPPORT WHERE PARTICIPANTS
CAN PROCESS THEIR EXPERIENCES IN WAYS THAT FEEL SAFE
AND AFFIRMING. THAT CARE SHOWS UP IN BOTH BIG
AND SMALL DETAILS CREATING AN ENVIRONMENT WHERE PEOPLE FEEL
GENUINELY WELCOMED. >> AS ELI GOULART IN FROM THE
SAN FRANCISCO OFFICE ON DISABILITY AND ACCESSIBILITY
HAS SHARED MIKA'S LEADERSHIP CENTERS ON ACCESS FOR ALL.
>> ROOTED IN CARE AND EMPOWERMENT, THEY CREATE
SPACES WHERE PEOPLE CAN SHOW UP AS THEIR FULL SELVES WHILE ALSO
MODELING WHAT IT MEANS TO LEAD THROUGH CONNECTION
AND COMMUNITY. >> MIKA'S LEADERSHIP IS
INFORMED BY DEEP EXPERIENCE IN COMMUNITY ORGANIZING
AND GLOBAL NONPROFIT WORK. IN 2011 THEY FOUNDED WHILE AS
DEEP AS A COMMUNITY CULTURAL CENTER IN MANAGUA, NICARAGUA,
WHICH CONTINUES TO PROVIDE MENTAL HEALTH AND GENDER
AFFIRMING SUPPORT FOR LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITIES ALONG WITH
CULTURAL AND EDUCATIONAL PROGRAMING.
THE IMPACT OF THAT WORK IS LASTING WITH YOUNG PEOPLE WHO
FIRST CONNECTED. THEY'RE NOW GROWING INTO
LEADERS THEMSELVES. >> ACROSS ALL OF THEIR WORK,
MIKA APPROACHES DISABILITY JUSTICE AS CULTURAL WORK
EMPHASIZING CARE AND THE UNDERSTANDING THAT ACCESS IS
SOMETHING THAT BENEFITS ALL OF US.
>> MIKA STORY IS A POWERFUL EXAMPLE OF WHAT IT MEANS TO
BUILD COMMUNITY ROOTED IN BELONGING.
>> THROUGH THEIR LEADERSHIP THEY THEY'RE NOT ONLY CREATING
SPACE BUT HELPING REDEFINE HOW OUR IN OUR CITY UNDERSTANDS
DISABILITY. MIKA THANK YOU FOR YOUR
LEADERSHIP AND YOUR COMMITMENT TO THE DISABILITY COMMUNITY
IN SAN FRANCISCO. YOUR WORK IS HELPING MAKE OUR
CITY MORE INCLUSIVE AND MORE JUST FOR THE RESIDENTS WE
SERVE. WE ARE GRATEFUL FOR EVERYTHING
YOU HAVE DONE AND LOOK FORWARD TO THE IMPACT YOU WILL CONTINUE
TO MAKE IN THE YEARS AHEAD. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMUD. >> WE'RE REALLY LUCKY TO HAVE A
LEADER WHO'S ONE OF US. >> AND I'M HUMBLED TO BE
RECOGNIZED TODAY. >> I'M SO GRATEFUL TO GET TO BE
PART OF THE DISABILITY CULTURAL CENTER HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND IT WOULDN'T BE POSSIBLE WITHOUT CITY LEADERS WHO
UNDERSTAND THE IMPORTANCE OF DISABILITY SPACES
AND DISABILITY CULTURE. AND I HAVE SEEN THAT NEED SO
CLEARLY. ONE COMMUNITY MEMBER PUT IT
BEAUTIFULLY WHEN THEY SAID AS A LOW INCOME TRANS DISABLED
PERSON OF COLOR. I FREQUENT THE DCC BECAUSE IT
IS A SPACE WHERE I FEEL SAFE TO UNMASK AND TO BE MY AUTHENTIC
AND UNAPOLOGETIC SELF. >> IT IS SUCH A PRIVILEGE TO BE
PART OF CO-CREATING THIS SPACE A SPACE THAT I DIDN'T FULLY
RECOGNIZE HOW MUCH I NEEDED TO .
>> AND THAT'S EXACTLY WHY WE'RE HERE FOR BECAUSE WE KNOW ALL
TOO WELL THAT IN OUR CURRENT REALITY BASIC RIGHTS
AND ACCEPTANCE AREN'T A GIVEN. >> WE HEARD AUTISM CALLED AN
EPIDEMIC AND A PREVENTABLE DISEASE BY THE U.S. SECRETARY
OF HEALTH AND HUMAN SERVICES WHILE DENYING ACTUAL EPIDEMICS.
>> IT'S ENOUGH TO MAKE ME NEED TO ADD A FOURTH WEIGHTED
BLANKET TO MY SLEEPING SET UP. >> SO LET THIS RECOGNITION BE
REFLECTED BACK TO OUR BEAUTIFUL COMMUNITY AS WE DO OUR BEST TO
CALM OUR NERVOUS SYSTEMS IN A WORLD THAT'S FAR TOO HARSH FOR
THEM. >> WHETHER YOU MASK ALL THE
TIME OR YOU DON'T HAVE IT IN YOU TO MASK IT ALL TO THOSE
WHO ARE DIAGNOSED AT THREE AND ALSO THOSE WHO ARE AFRAID
TO SEEK A DIAGNOSIS IN THIS POLITICAL CLIMATE FOR THE BLACK
BROWN TRANS AND AFIB FOLKS WHO ARE OVERLOOKED OR NOT BELIEVED.
>> AND FOR THOSE WITH HIGH SUPPORT NEEDS IN A CAPITALIST
ECONOMY YOU DESERVE NOT JUST ACCEPTANCE.
YOU DESERVE RESPECT AND HUMAN RIGHTS AND CARE AND BELONGING
AND LOVE. >> A FRIEND TOLD ME RECENTLY
THAT HE'S TRYING TO CHANNEL OUR BELOVED ANCESTOR ALICE WONG
AND LEAD WITH LOVE FOR ME. >> LEADING WITH LOVE MEANS
UPLIFTING THE BRILLIANCE IN OUR DISABILITY COMMUNITY.
>> AND IT ALSO MEANS BRINGING SOMEONE A HEATED BLANKET OR A
MASK OR A PAIR OF EARPLUGS OR A PIECE OF VEGAN CHOCOLATE CAKE
WHILE DRESSED IN A COOKIE MONSTER OR RACCOON ONESIE.
>> IT MEANS UNMASKING TOGETHER .
>> SO I JUST WANT TO SAY I LOVE HOW YOUR BRAIN WORKS.
YOU ARE NOT TOO MUCH AND YOU ARE ENOUGH.
>> JUST AS YOU ARE. YOU DESERVE ALL THE LOVE IN THE
WORLD. >> AND I'LL END AS ALICE OFTEN
DID WITH ONE MORE EXPRESSION OF LOVE.
>> THANK YOU ALL SO MUCH. AND FREE PALESTINE
. DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
COLLEAGUES, IT IS MY PRIVILEGE TODAY TO HONOR VAL COUNT
APPALLING. I'M SORRY VAL CAN A PAROLEE A
MAN WHO HAS BEEN INTEGRAL TO THE EVOLUTION OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BALLET INTO A WORLD CLASS ARTISTIC AND CULTURAL
TREASURE? >> VAL.
COME ON UP TO THE LECTERN. VAL.
>> VAL. KEN A PAROLEE WAS BORN
IN RENTON, WASHINGTON AND STUDIED MUSIC AND THEATER
AT WASHINGTON STATE UNIVERSITY WHILE STUDYING AT WSU.
HE TOOK A BALLET WORKSHOP WHERE HIS TALENT WAS NOTICED
IMMEDIATELY. HE WAS OFFERED A FORD
FOUNDATION SCHOLARSHIP IN 1972 AND BEGAN HIS BALLET TRAINING
AT THE SAN FRANCISCO BALLET SCHOOL.
AFTER ONLY A YEAR AND A HALF INTO HIS STUDIES HE WAS OFFERED
A CONTRACT WITH THE COMPANY WHERE HE WOULD DANCE FOR THE
NEXT 53 CONSECUTIVE SEASONS. VAL ROSE THROUGH THE RANKS
AND QUICKLY BECAME A LEAD DANCER UNDER THE CO-DIRECTOR
SHIP OF LOU CHRISTENSEN AND MICHAEL SPOON AND WAS
EVENTUALLY NAMED AS THE COMPANY'S RESIDENT
CHOREOGRAPHER. OVER THE YEARS HE HAS SERVED AS
A PRINCIPAL CHARACTER DANCER AND REHEARSAL DIRECTOR.
I MYSELF HAVE SEEN YOU PERFORM MANY TIMES AS UNCLE DRESSMAKER
IN THE NUTCRACKER WHERE MY GODDAUGHTER HAS PERFORMED FOR
MANY YEARS. VAL HAS WORKED WITH ARTISTIC
DIRECTORS HELGI THOMPSON, TAMARA ROJO AND PERFORMED WITH
CARROLL CHOREOGRAPHERS INCLUDING GEORGE BALANCHINE,
JEROME ROBBINS, WILLIAM FORSYTH, PAUL TAYLOR, FREDERICK
ASHTON, KENNETH MCMILLAN, ARTHUR PITA, YURI PERSICO
AND MANY OTHERS. AS HE STEPS AWAY FROM THE WAR
MEMORIAL STAGE AS A PERFORMER VAL IS NOWHERE NEAR THE END OF
HIS ARTIST. HIS IMPRESSIVE ARTISTIC CAREER
AND AS THE SAN FRANCISCO CHRONICLE MADE CLEAR IN THE
FIRST PARAGRAPH OF ITS OWN STORY UNVEILS DECISION TO STEP
AWAY FROM THE STAGE. HE ISN'T RETIRING.
VAL HAS CREATED HUNDREDS OF BALLETS FOR COMPANIES ALL OVER
THE WORLD, INCLUDING 25 PIECES FOR THE DANCERS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BALLET AS WELL AS WORKS PERFORMED BY THE SMALL
AND CONTEMPORARY BALLET HONG KONG BALLET, SCOTTISH BALLET,
THE JOFFREY BALLET PACIFIC NORTHWEST BALLET THEATER,
LOUISVILLE BALLET. RICHMOND BALLET AND BALLET WEST
AND MORE. HIS BALLET LUMBAR LUMBAR ARENA
WAS EVEN PERFORMED BY BALLERINA SISTERS LORENA AND LORNA FAY
WHO ON SESAME STREET WHEN COVID 19 STRUCK AND SHUTTERED
THEATERS AROUND THE WORLD VALKYRIE ADDED A NEW FULL
LENGTH PRODUCTION OF JEKYLL AND HYDE FOR THE FINNISH
NATIONAL BALLET. WORKING WITH DANCERS IN FINLAND
AS HE CHOREOGRAPH HALF THEIR STEPS FROM SAN FRANCISCO OVER
ZOOM, HIS LATEST PROJECT IS THE NEW PRODUCTION OF COPPELIA SET
TO PREMIERE WITH THE NATIONAL BALLET OF CANADA IN THE SPRING
OF 2027. VAL ON BEHALF OF GRATEFUL BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS, CONGRATULATIONS ON A LONG CAREER AS A DANCER
WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO BALLET AND BEST OF LUCK FROM US TO YOU
ON ALL OF YOUR FUTURE CREATIONS .
THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY
AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THIS IS QUITE AN HONOR. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
I DON'T KNOW IF YOU REMEMBER MOST OF ARE TOO YOUNG BUT
REMEMBER THIS SONG IF YOU'RE GOING TO SAN FRANCISCO WHERE
FLOWERS IN YOUR HAIR 1967 I WAS OBSESSED WITH THAT AS A
SOPHOMORE IN HIGH SCHOOL AND I KNEW I WAS GOING TO MOVE HERE
AND I WHO WOULD HAVE KNOWN THAT IN 1972 THAT DREAM OR OBSESSION
WOULD COME TRUE? I'M SO GRATEFUL FOR MY 54 YEARS
AT SAN FRANCISCO BALLET AND ALL OF THE EXPERIENCES AS A DANCER,
CHOREOGRAPHER, REHEARSAL ASSISTANT AND I'VE BUILT A MANY
RELATIONSHIPS ALONG THE WAY WITH THAT HAVE GONE ON THE
JOURNEY WITH ME. SOME OF THEM ARE HERE WITH US
TODAY WHICH I TOTALLY APPRECIATE.
THANK YOU. AND I'VE BEEN I WOULD LIKE TO
THANK NOT ONLY THE ARTISTIC STAFF THAT I'VE WORKED WITH BUT
WHICH INCLUDES. MIND YOU I WAS HERE 54 YEARS.
THE COMPANY'S 93 YEARS. I'VE BEEN WITH FIVE ARTISTIC
DIRECTORS. I WANT TO THANK THEM.
WILLEM CHRISTIAN LOU CHRISTIANSEN, MICHAEL SMEE
UNHEALTHY THOMAS AND AND TO MY ARROYO THEY'VE ALL KEPT ME ON
WHICH IS I'M SO GRATEFUL FOR BUT ALSO REALLY GRATEFUL TO ALL
THE MUSICIANS STAGE CREW SET AND COSTUME DESIGNERS,
ADMINISTRATIVE STAFF, BOARD MEMBERS, COMPOSERS, POP MASTERS
AND PARTICULARLY THE DANCERS WHO HAVE SHARED THE STAGE WITH
AND CREATED ON THEM. I'VE BEEN ONE OF THE LUCKIEST
PEOPLE IN THE WORLD. WELL YOU WON'T SEE ME ON STAGE
ANYMORE. I'M BOOKING AS A CHOREOGRAPHER
MORE THAN EVER IN THE BAY AREA AS WELL AS WORLDWIDE WHICH I
AGAIN I'M ONE OF THE LUCKIEST PEOPLE IN THE WORLD AND I GET
TO LIVE IN SAN FRANCISCO. WELL, YOU WON'T SEE ME ON THAT
STAGE. YOU KNOW I WILL BE
CHOREOGRAPHING QUITE OFTEN SAN FRANCISCO HAS BEEN MY HOME FOR
MORE THAN HALF A CENTURY AND I'M SO GRATEFUL AND FEEL
PRIVILEGED TO BE ABLE TO LIVE HERE AND BE IN A CITY THAT
APPRECIATES THE ARTS, FUNDS, THE ARTS AND BECAUSE ARTS ARE
SO ESSENTIAL FOR ANY CITY AND IT'S A WORLD CLASS CITY
SOME OF WHICH IS BECAUSE OF THE ARTS AND THE SUPPORT OF IT, THE
CITY CONTINUES INSPIRED ME AND I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUED
CREATE AND CHOREOGRAPH HERE. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU
. >> ALL THESE PEOPLE DISTRICT
TEN SUPERVISOR WALTON. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
PRESIDENT MOUNTAIN AND COLLEAGUES TODAY I RISE TO
HONOR SAM DODGE. WE WANT TO PROUDLY HONOR A
PUBLIC SERVANT WHOSE IMPACT ON SAN FRANCISCO CAN BE SEEN
IN EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD, EVERY COORDINATED RESPONSE AND EVERY
LIFE TOUCHED THROUGH COMPASSION IN ACTION.
TODAY WE RECOGNIZE, SAM, THAT FOR NEARLY 12 YEARS OF
EXTRAORDINARY SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND FOR A LIFETIME DEDICATED TO HELPING PEOPLE WHO
ARE TOO OFTEN OVERLOOKED. >> SAM BUILT A CAREER BY TAKING
ON THE CITY'S HARDEST CHALLENGES AND THE JOBS FEW
OTHERS WERE WILLING TO DO. HE DID NOT SEEK EASIEST
ASSIGNMENTS OR PUBLIC PRAISE. INSTEAD HE STEPPED INTO CRISIS.
COMPLEXITY AND CONTROVERSY WITH DETERMINATION, VISION AND HEART
. THROUGHOUT HIS SERVICE TO SAN
FRANCISCO, SAM BECAME ONE OF THE CITY'S LEADING ARCHITECTS
OF INNOVATIVE HOMELESSNESS RESPONSE SYSTEMS AS A KEY
LEADER IN THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOPE, THE DEPARTMENT OF
HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING, PUBLIC WORKS AND THE
DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT.
SAM HELPED SHAPED HOW THIS CITY RESPONDS TO UNHOUSED RESIDENTS
WITH DIGNITY AND URGENCY. HE WAS INSTRUMENTAL IN CREATING
SAN FRANCISCO'S FIRST NAVIGATION CENTER TRANSFORMING
THE SHELTER MODEL AND OFFERING A PATH TO STABILITY FOR
THOUSANDS. HE DESIGNED AND LAUNCHED THE
PIT STOP PUBLIC TOILET PROGRAM. >> NOW A NATIONALLY RECOGNIZED
MODEL THAT HAS SERVED HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE WHILE
IMPROVING PUBLIC HEALTH CITYWIDE HE FOUNDED AND LED THE
HEALTHY STREETS OPERATION CENTER, BRINGING TOGETHER
MULTIPLE DEPARTMENTS TO COORDINATE HUMANE AND EFFECTIVE
RESPONSES TO ENCAMPMENTS AND STREET CRISES.
MOST RECENTLY AS DIRECTOR OF STREET RESPONSE COORDINATION,
SAM BUILT AN ENTIRELY NEW DIVISION AT THE DEPARTMENT OF
EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT OVERSEEING INTERAGENCY SEA OPERATIONS THAT
SIGNIFICANTLY REDUCED ENCAMPMENT ACTIVITY, IMPROVED
EMERGENCY RESPONSE TIMES AND CREATED A STRONGER SYSTEMS
OF CARE. HE HELPED LAUNCH THE HEART
RESPONSE TEAM FOR POLICE AND FIRE RESOURCES WHILE
CONNECTING VULNERABLE RESIDENTS TO SERVICES.
HE ALSO SERVED AS A FOUNDING LEADER OF THE DRUG MARKET
AGENCY COORDINATION CENTER CONFRONTING ONE OF THE CITY'S
MOST URGENT PUBLIC SAFETY CRISES.
>> BUT BEYOND THE TITLES AND PROGRAMS, SAM'S GREATEST
LEGACY IS HIS WILLINGNESS TO DO THE HARD WORK OF GOVERNMENT
WITH EMPATHY. HE UNDERSTOOD THAT BEHIND EVERY
POLICY DEBATE WAS A HUMAN BEING IN THE BEHIND EVERY STATISTIC
WAS A PERSON DESERVING DIGNITY. >> THIS VICTIM WAS ESPECIALLY
MISS SAM STEFANSKI COMMITMENT BECAUSE NO MATTER THE HOUR OR
THE CHALLENGE HE WAS ALWAYS AVAILABLE, RESPONSIVE AND READY
TO HELP OUR TEAM SOLVE PROBLEMS FOR COMMUNITY.
>> HIS CARE CAREER REFLECTS A SIMPLE BUT POWERFUL TRUTH.
PROGRESS HAPPENS WHEN COURAGEOUS PEOPLE ARE WILLING
TO SERVE. SO TODAY WE EXTEND OUR DEEPEST
GRATITUDE TO SAM DASH FOR HIS LEADERSHIP INNOVATION,
TOUGHNESS, COMPASSION AND UNWAVERING COMMITMENT TO
MAKING THIS CITY BETTER FOR ALL.
THANK YOU, SAM, FOR YOUR YEARS OF SERVICE AND FOR LEAVING SAN
FRANCISCO STRONGER THAN YOU FOUND IT.
>> THANK YOU FOR BUT WAIT BECAUSE SAM DODGE YOU HAVE FANS
AS A SUPERVISOR. >> CHERYL.
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MAN WOMAN SUPERVISOR WALTON, THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR HONORING AN INCREDIBLE PUBLIC SERVANT.
SAM. SUPERVISOR WALTON SPOKE ABOUT
YOU PERFECTLY AND SO I WON'T REPEAT THAT.
BUT ON A PERSONAL NOTE I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR
PATIENCE AND YOUR GRACIOUSNESS AND YOUR KINDNESS TO ME WHEN WE
MET ALMOST FOUR YEARS AGO. I PROBABLY KNEW LESS THAN
NOTHING AND YOU TAUGHT ME WHAT IT MEANS TO BE A PUBLIC SERVANT
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, WHAT IT MEANS TO BE AGGRESSIVELY
COMPASSIONATE IN SERVING PEOPLE WHO WANT A BETTER LIFE AND HOW
WE HERE IN CITY GOVERNMENT ARE HERE TO SOLVE PROBLEMS.
>> AND I CAN SEE ME OUT IN THE AUDIENCE SO MANY OF YOUR
COLLEAGUES WHO I'VE ALSO BEEN LUCKY TO WORK ALONGSIDE AND I
THINK THEIR PRESENCE HERE SPEAKS TO TO IT JUST AS WELL.
YOU ARE A KIND, THOUGHTFUL AND SMART PERSON.
WE ARE SO LUCKY FOR YOU. I AM SO LUCKY FOR YOU ON A
PERSONAL LEVEL AND I JUST WANT TO JUST THANK YOU FROM ME STEVE
NOT AS A SUPERVISOR BUT JUST FOR ME.
>> THANK YOU. THANK SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WALTON
FOR HONORING SAM. >> SAM, I'VE BEEN MISSING YOU.
YOU KNOW, AS SUPERVISOR WALTON HAS STATED, YOU KNOW, PUBLIC
SERVANTS DO A LOT. THEY DO A LOT THAT IS NOT SEEN
AND YOU DID MUCH MORE THAN MOST .
YOU RESPONDED IMMEDIATELY WITH THOUGHTFULNESS, WITH EMPATHY
AND WITH SMARTS. YOU KNOW, YOU WERE STRATEGIC
AND LOGICAL AND YOU ALWAYS SOUGHT TO UNDERSTAND PEOPLE'S
SITUATIONS AND MEET THEM WHERE THEY WERE AT TO GET TO OUR
PUBLIC POLICY GOALS AND I HAVE SO APPRECIATED THE PARTNERSHIP
YOUR RESPONSIVENESS TO THE DISTRICT SEVEN OFFICE TO ME
PERSONALLY FOR EVERYTHING YOU'VE DONE I THANK YOU FOR
WHAT YOU'VE DONE FOR PEOPLE AND FOR THE CITY AND COUNTY OF
SAN FRANCISCO. >> WE REALLY APPRECIATE YOU.
Q THANK THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANKS SUPERVISOR WALTON
I'M VERY GLAD THAT YOU DID THIS.
>> I THINK ANY OF US WHO HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO WORK WITH
SAM ARE GRATEFUL AND EACH OF OUR OWN WAYS EACH OF OUR OWN
DISTRICTS HAD DIFFERENT CHALLENGES.
AND SAM, YOU HAD A WILD, WILD RIDE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SO FROM THE NAVIGATION CENTER DAYS TO THE PANDEMIC TO
THE DEMAK LOTS AND LOTS OF DIFFERENT STRATEGIES, LOTS
AND LOTS OF DIFFERENT DEMANDS COMING AT YOU FROM LOTS
AND LOTS OF DIFFERENT PEOPLE SOMETIMES PUSHING YOU IN ALL
SORTS OF DIFFERENT DIRECTIONS. I ALWAYS FOUND YOU TO BE, YOU
KNOW, A GREAT PARTNER AND WE YOU KNOW, YOU DID SOME GREAT
THINGS IN THE CASTRO. I WAS GLAD TO BE ABLE TO WORK
WITH YOU ON SOME OF THAT ON SOME OF THAT AND YOU WERE
ALWAYS THE OTHER THING THAT JUST YOU KNOW, YOU WERE ALWAYS
ATTUNED TO THE NEEDS OF THE COMMUNITY AND AND RESPONSIVE TO
THAT. YOU ALSO WERE WORRIED ABOUT THE
THE ACTUAL HUMAN BEINGS ON THE STREET AND THAT WAS IT CAME
THROUGH AND I REALLY APPRECIATED IT.
SO THANK YOU FOR YOUR WORK. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON PRESIDENT
MEDLIN THE FULL BOARD. THANK YOU.
THIS IS ONE OF THE MOST MEANINGFUL RECOGNITIONS IN MY
CAREER AND I'M GENUINELY MOVED TO RECEIVE IT FROM YOU FROM
AND FROM THIS BODY AS A WHOLE. I WANT TO START BY INTRODUCING
TWO PEOPLE WHO ARE HERE WITH ME TODAY.
>> MY WIFE HEATHER DUTCH WHO HAS LIVED ALONGSIDE THIS WORK I
HAVE FOR ALL OF IT THROUGH EVERY LATE NIGHT AND HARD WEEK
AND MOMENT OF DOUBT AND WHO NEVER ONCE ASKED ME TO DO
ANYTHING OTHER THAN TO KEEP GOING.
HEATHER I LOVE YOU AND THANK YOU.
>> I'M ALSO LUCKY TO BE JOINED HERE TODAY AMONG OTHER PEOPLE
BY DALE SEYMOUR, FOUNDER OF CODE TENDERLOIN AND LONGTIME
CHAIR OF THE LOCAL MASS COORDINATING BOARD.
>> DILLON I HAVE FRIENDS BUT WE GO BACK A LONG WAY.
>> THERE WAS A TIME WHEN DALE WAS A CLIENT OF MINE A MAN
NAVIGATING HOMELESSNESS IN ONE OF THE HARDEST NEIGHBORHOODS
IN ONE OF THE MOST EXPENSIVE CITIES IN THE WORLD.
I GOT TO PLAY A SMALL PART IN THAT CHAPTER OF HIS STORY
AND THEN I GOT TO WATCH HIM WRITE THE REST OF IT HIMSELF
FOUNDING AN ORGANIZATION THAT HAS TRAINED THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE
RESTORING DIGNITY ONE PERSON AT A TIME IN A NEIGHBORHOOD THAT
HE LOVES AND BECOMING ONE OF THE MOST RESPECTED ADVOCATES
IN THE CITY. DALE THE HONOR OF KNOWING YOU
IS ENTIRELY MINE. YOU'RE THE REASON I KEEP DOING
THIS WORK. YOU AND PEOPLE LIKE YOU.
>> I MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO 28 YEARS AGO THIS JULY.
I CAME KNOWING EXACTLY WHAT I WAS LOOKING FOR AND SOON AFTER
A COUPLE OF YEARS I FOUND IT IN AN UNLIKELY PLACE IN THE
TENDERLOIN AT THE TENDERLOIN HOUSING CLINIC ORGANIZING
TENANTS, PREVENTING EVICTIONS AND TRYING TO KEEP PEOPLE
IN THEIR HOMES. THAT WORKED FOR ME.
THE MOST IMPORTANT THING I KNOW THE PEOPLE WE SERVE ARE NOT
PROBLEMS TO BE MANAGED. >> THEIR NEIGHBORS WHO KNOW THE
SOLUTIONS THEY ARE PEOPLE IN THE MIDDLE OF A STORY AND WE
GET THE PRIVILEGE OF BEING PART OF HOW THAT TURNS OUT.
>> FROM THE TENDERLOIN HOUSING CLINIC I WENT TO NEW YORK CITY
TO THE CITY'S DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESS SERVICES AND THEN I
CAME BACK HOME TO SAN FRANCISCO TO CITY GOVERNMENT WHERE I NOW
HAVE THE HONOR OF SERVING FOR 12 YEARS, 12 YEARS WORKING ON
PROJECTS WITH NEARLY EVERY DEPARTMENT AND AGENCY.
>> THIS CITY HAS. >> I WANT TO SAY SOMETHING
CLEARLY BECAUSE IT DOESN'T GET SAID NEARLY ENOUGH.
EVERY CORNER OF THIS CITY GOVERNMENT I FOUND TALENTED,
DEDICATED AND DEEPLY COMMITTED PEOPLE PEOPLE WHO SHOWED UP
EVERY DAY IN CONDITIONS THEY WERE OFTEN DIFFICULT, SOMETIMES
DANGEROUS OR EVEN DEADLY. AND ALMOST ALWAYS THANKLESS.
THE PEOPLE OF PUBLIC WORKS AT THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
AT HCA, AT HCA, THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT MTA 311
S.F. PD AND THE FIRE DEPARTMENT.
THEY ARE WHAT MAKES THIS CITY FUNCTION.
THIS COMMENDATION BELONGS TO THEM AS MUCH AS IT BELONGS TO
ME. IN 12 YEARS I'VE HAD THE CHANCE
TO HELP BUILD SOME THINGS I'M PROUD OF.
SUPERVISOR WALTON NAMES A LOT OF THEM AND THERE'S MORE.
BUT THE NAVIGATION CENTER MODEL THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS
AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING, THE PITSTOP PROGRAM, THE HEALTHY
STREETS OPERATION CENTER AND THE MAC THE HEART TEAM A
RECORD INCREASE IN FEDERAL HOUSING FUNDS THOUSANDS OF NEW
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING UNITS. THE FIRST ADULT LGBTQ CENTER
SHELTER AND OUR SAFETY AMBASSADOR PROGRAM DEDICATED
PEOPLE AT THE GROUND TO NEIGHBORHOODS ACROSS THE CITY
BUILDING RELATIONSHIPS, DE-ESCALATING, CONNECTING WITH
PEOPLE TO SERVICES. AMBASSADORS ARE NOT A FOOTNOTE
TO THIS WORK IN THE FRONT LINES OF IT EVERY SINGLE DAY DOING
EXACTLY WHAT THIS CITY ASKS ITS MOST COMMITTED PEOPLE TO DO
SHOW UP, BE PRESENT AND TREAT EVERY PERSON THEY MEET WITH
DIGNITY. I WANT TO BE HONEST WITH YOU.
NONE OF THESE PROGRAMS OR WHAT I THINK ABOUT WHEN I THINK
ABOUT THIS WORK WHAT I THINK ABOUT IS THE INDIVIDUAL PEOPLE
BOTH WORKING AND AND CHANGING THEIR LIVES.
A MAN WHO HAS BEEN SLEEPING OUTSIDE FOR A DECADE AND THEN
WASN'T A WOMAN WHO FINALLY FELT SAFE ENOUGH TO SLEEP INDOORS.
>> THE MOMENT ALMOST THE MOMENT INVISIBLE TO MOST WHEN
SOMEONE'S LIFE SHIFTS DIRECTION .
THOSE MOMENTS ARE UNDER APPRECIATED.
THE WORKERS WHO CREATE THEM THE OUTREACH WORKERS, CASE
MANAGERS, SHELTERS, STAFFS, AMBASSADORS WALKING THE SAME
BLOCK DAY AFTER DAY. >> THE PEOPLE WHO SIT WITH
SOMEONE IN CRISIS AND SAY I SEE YOU AND WE CAN WORK THIS OUT
TOGETHER. >> ARE THE WHOLE POINT THEY
OFTEN DON'T END UP IN THIS PODIUM BUT WE'RE HERE TOGETHER
TODAY. I ALSO WANT TO SAY THIS WE HAVE
A DUTY TO CARE FOR ONE ANOTHER NOT AS A SLOGAN, AS A DAILY
PRACTICE. THE MEASURE OF A CITY IS NOT
ITS SKYLINE OR ITS WEALTH. IT'S HOW IT TREATS A PERSON
SLEEPING IN A DOORWAY. >> SAN FRANCISCO IN PERFECTLY
YET PERSISTENTLY HAS CHOSEN TO TURN TOWARDS THAT PERSON RATHER
THAN AWAY FROM THEM. I HAVE BEEN HONORED TO BE PART
OF THAT CHOICE ALL THESE YEARS .
>> I'M GRATEFUL TO SUPERVISOR WALDEN AND THE DISTRICT TEN
OFFICE AND ALL YOUR OFFICES FOR SEEING THIS WORK AND HONORING
IT. I'M GRATEFUL TO THIS CITY FOR
LETTING ME SERVANT, FOR TEACHING ME AND FOR NEVER
LETTING ME LOOK AWAY AND I'M NOT FINISHED YET.
THIS WORK WILL CONTINUE. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
AND IF YOU WANT TO COME ON INTO THE WELL
. ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, I THINK
WE GO BACK TO ITEM 23 NOW ITEM 23 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO AUTHORIZE THE SAN FRANCISCO
MUNICIPAL TRANSPORTATION AGENCY TO ESTABLISH A CURBSIDE
ELECTRIC VEHICLE CHARGING STATION PERMIT PROGRAM FOR THE
INSTALLATION AND OPERATION OF CURBSIDE ELECTRIC VEHICLE
CHARGING ON CITY SIDEWALKS AND TO PROVIDE THAT PERMITTEES
ARE NOT REQUIRED TO OBTAIN A SIDEWALK ENCROACHMENT PERMIT
FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS TO FURTHER AMEND THE
PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO REFLECT THE AUTHORITY OF THE S.F. MTA
TO ISSUE PERMITS FOR THE CURBSIDE ELECTRIC VEHICLE
CHARGING STATION PROGRAM AND TO AMEND THE TRANSPORTATION CODE
TO AUTHORIZE THE MTA TO IMPOSE ADMINISTRATIVE PENALTIES FOR
VIOLATIONS OF ELECTRIC VEHICLE CHARGING STATION PERMITS.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 23 SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON ABSENT SUPERVISOR WONG HAI WONG
EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN SUPERVISOR MANDEL I SUPERVISOR AMILCAR
MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER I THERE ARE NINE EYES
AND ONE ABSENCE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 24 ITEM
24 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO SUPPORT CALIFORNIA STATE
ASSEMBLY BILL NUMBER 2276 INTRODUCED BY ASSEMBLY MEMBER
ESMERALDA SORIA WHICH WILL ESTABLISH A PILOT PROGRAM
REQUIRING THE INSTALLATION OF ACTIVE INTELLIGENT SPEED
ASSISTANCE DRIVE A DEVICE FOR DRIVERS CONVICTED OF SEVERE
SPEEDING RELATED TO OFFENSES IN SELECT CALIFORNIA COUNTIES.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 24 SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SAUDER SAUDER I THERE ARE TEN EYES
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 25 THROUGH 37 TOGETHER YES ITEMS
25 THROUGH 37 ARE 13 RESOLUTIONS THAT INITIATE
LANDMARK DESIGNATION FOR ITEM 25.
THIS IS FOR THE CALIFORNIA MASONIC MEMORIAL TEMPLE LOCATED
AT 1111 THROUGH 1171 CALIFORNIA STREET.
ITEM 26 IS FOR PINOCCHIO'S LOCATED AT 500 THROUGH 508
BROADWAY. ITEM 27 IS FOR FOOD GANCI
BUILDING LOCATED AT 678 GREEN STREET.
ITEM 28 IS FOR THE GEORGE PERRIN HOUSE LOCATED AT 535
POWELL STREET. ITEM 29 IS FOR THE GREAT CHINA
THEATER LOCATED AT 626 THROUGH 638 JACKSON STREET.
ITEM 30 IS FOR THE ITALIAN-AMERICAN CLUB LOCATED
AT 1630 STOCKTON STREET. ITEM 31 IS FOR THE MAYBACH
BUILDING LOCATED AT 1736 STOCKTON STREET.
ITEM 32 IS FOR MONA'S CANDLE LIGHT LOCATED AT 463 THROUGH
473 BROADWAY. ITEM 33 IS FOR THE NAME CLUE
SCHOOL LOCATED AT 750 FIVE SACRAMENTO STREET.
ITEM 34 IS FOR THE OLD FIRST PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH.
ITEM 35 IS FOR THE TRANSAMERICA PYRAMID LOCATED AT 600
MONTGOMERY STREET. ITEM THREE IS FOR THE
UNIVERSITY CLUB LOCATED AT 800 POWELL STREET.
ITEM 37 IS FOR THE VESUVIO CAFE BUILDING LOCATED AT 253
COLUMBUS AVENUE. >> SUPERVISOR SUTTER, THANK
YOU, PRESIDENT. I HOPE WE'LL HAVE YOUR SUPPORT
FOR 25 THROUGH 37 ALTHOUGH ON 29 WE NEED A LITTLE BIT MORE
TIME TO WORK ON THAT PARTICULAR ITEM.
SO I WOULD ASK AND MAKE A MOTION THAT WE SEND 29 WE REFER
THAT BACK TO LAND USE AS READ SUTTER HAS MADE A MOTION TO
REFER ITEM 29 TO LAND USE COMMITTEE.
IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY CHERYL?
COLLEAGUES CAN WE TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION?
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED AND THEN MADAM CLERK,
COULD YOU CALL THE ROLL ON OR ACTUALLY WE DON'T NEED TO CALL
THE ROLL. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THE
REMAINING ITEMS THAT IS EVERYTHING FROM 25 TO 37
EXCLUDING 29. SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> AND MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 38 ITEM 38 THIS IS A
MOTION TO APPOINT JOHN MA TO THE SUGARY DRINKS DISTRIBUTOR
TAX ADVISORY COMMITTEE TERM ENDING DECEMBER 31ST 2026.
>> SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS A.
WHOOPS SOMEONE JUST GO ON THE ROLL.
>> OKAY. SUPERVISOR DORSEY I JUST DON'T
WANT TO LET THE MOMENT PASS OF SAYING WHAT A BIG FAN I AM OF
JOHN MARS JUST BECAUSE I HAVE WORKED WITH HIM GOING BACK ON
TOBACCO-FREE KIDS AND SOME OF THE THINGS THAT WE HAVE DONE
AND I'M JUST A FAN AND THIS IS A PARTICULARLY ENTHUSIASTIC
VOTE TODAY. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
39 AND 40 TOGETHER ITEMS 39 AND 40 ARE TWO MOTIONS TO
APPROVE TO ME ORAL NOMINATION MEANS TO REAPPOINT MEMBERS TO
THE TREASURE ISLAND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY BOARD OF DIRECTORS
ITEM 39 A REAPPOINT TIMOTHY RUFE FOR A TERM ENDING FEBRUARY
26TH, 2030. MY APOLOGIES IF I MISPRONOUNCED
THAT ITEM 40 REAPPOINT LINDA FOR DICKEY RICHARDSON AND FOR A
TERM ENDING APRIL 28TH 2030. >> AND AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION.
>> MR. PRESIDENT, BEFORE YOU GAVEL DOWN.
GOOD LORD DARCY SO I CAN'T LET THEM ALL I AM A FAN OF BOTH OF
THESE TWO AND I REALIZE I SHOULDN'T I SHOULD NEVER DO
THIS BUT LINDA HAS BEEN TERRIFIC AT THE TREASURE ISLAND
AND I'M A FAN OF TIM'S AS WELL SO I FEEL NOW NOW I FEEL GUILTY
FOR LEAVING PEOPLE OUT. >> I'M HAPPY TO SUPPORT THEM
BOTH. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
MOTIONS ARE APPROVED. >> AND MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO
A ROLL CALL SUPERVISOR SIR CHERYL, YOUR FIRST UP TO
INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS. SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON.
THANK YOU, MADAM. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM AS WE COME TOGETHER
TO HONOR THE LIFE AND LEGACY OF DWAYNE GAINES SENIOR A BELOVED
COMMUNITY LEADER, SERVANT AND ADVOCATE WHOSE IMPACT WILL
BE FELT IN THE COMMUNITY FOR GENERATIONS TO COME.
DWAYNE GAINES EMBODIED THE PRINCIPLE LOVE THY NEIGHBOR AS
THYSELF. HE DID NOT SIMPLY SPEAK THOSE
WORDS. HE LIVED THEM EACH AND EVERY
DAY. THROUGH HIS UNWAVERING
COMMITMENT TO SERVICE. HE POURED HIS TIME, ENERGY
AND HEART INTO UPLIFTING OTHERS ESPECIALLY THOSE TOO OFTEN
OVERLOOKED OR LEFT BEHIND. >> HE WAS KNOWN THROUGHOUT OUR
COMMUNITIES AS SOMEONE WHO SHOWED UP WHETHER FEEDING
FAMILIES IN NEED, SUPPORTING RESIDENTS THROUGH HARDSHIP OR
STANDING IN THE GAP DURING TIMES OF CRISIS.
DWAYNE LED WITH COMPASSION AND ACTION.
HIS LEADERSHIP WAS NEVER PERFORMATIVE.
IT WAS PERSONAL. VISIBLE AND TRANSFORMATIVE.
HE ALSO DEDICATED HIMSELF TO INTERRUPTING CYCLES OF
VIOLENCE, PROTECTING THE LIVES OF YOUNG PEOPLE AND HELPING
NEIGHBORHOODS HEAL FROM GENERATIONS OF PAIN AND TRAUMA
. >> HE BELIEVED EVERY LIFE HAD
VALUE EVERY PERSON DESERVED DIGNITY AND EVERY COMMUNITY
DESERVED HOPE. >> DWAYNE GAINES SENIOR LEAVES
BEHIND MORE THAN MEMORIES. HE LEAVES BEHIND A BLUEPRINT
FOR WHAT TRUE COMMUNITY LEADERSHIP LOOKS LIKE A LEGACY
ROOTED IN LOVE. ACCOUNTABILITY, SERVICE
AND FAITH IN PEOPLE. TODAY WE HONOR NOT ONLY THE MAN
HE WAS BUT THE COUNTLESS LIVES HE TOUCHED AND THE STRONGER
CITY HE HELPED BUILD. MAY WE CONTINUE HIS WORK, CARRY
FORWARD HIS SPIRIT AND NEVER FORGET THE EXAMPLE HE SET FOR
ALL OF US. MAY DWAYNE GAINES, SENIOR.
REST IN POWER AND EVERLASTING PEACE AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> SUPERVISOR WONG. SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR CHAN. SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SIR CHEN ALL RIGHT
WILL COME SOUP PROVIDES FOR CHEN.
>> ROLL CALL. >> YES.
THANK YOU MADAM CARD. >> HELLO, COLLEAGUES.
I'M. I AM INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
TODAY TO CELEBRATE MAY 2026 AS ASIAN-AMERICAN AND PACIFIC
ISLANDER HERITAGE MONTH IN SAN FRANCISCO A TIME TO HONOR THE
RICH HISTORIES, CULTURES AND ENDURING CONTRIBUTION OF
OUR AAPI COMMUNITIES. THE MONTH OF MAY HOST DEEP
HISTORICAL SIGNIFICANCE. >> IT MARKS BOTH THE ARRIVAL OF
THE FIRST RECORDED JAPANESE IMMIGRANTS IN 1843 AND THE
COMPLETION AFTER TRANS CONTINENTAL RAILROAD IN 1869 AN
ACHIEVEMENT MADE POSSIBLE LARGELY THROUGH THE LABOR OF
CHINESE WORKERS WHO PRESERVED IT UNDER HARSH AND UNJUST
CONDITIONS. WHAT BEGAN DECADES AGO AS A
CALL FOR VISIBILITY HAS GROWN INTO A NATIONWIDE OBSERVANCE
NOW IN ITS 22ND YEAR. THE AP HERITAGE FOUNDATION'S
THEME IS TWO ELEVATING CULTURES HIGHLIGHTING THE BEAUTY
AND DIVERSITY OF AAPI TRADITIONS FROM ART
AND LITERATURE TO FOOD PERFORMANCES AND COMMUNITY STAR
STORYTELLING. THERE ARE OVER 100 EVENTS
TAKING PLACE ACROSS THE CITY THIS IN MAY.
WE ARE EXCITED TO KICK OFF THE MONTH ON MAY 6TH WITH THE APA
HERITAGE AWARDS AND COMMUNITY GALA.
THIS SPECIAL EVENING WILL HONOR OUTSTANDING ORGANIZATIONS
AND YOUTH LEADERS AND SHOWCASE CULTURAL PERFORMANCES THAT
REFLECT THE VIBRANCY OF OUR COMMUNITY OF OUR COMMUNITIES.
THANK YOU TO CLAUDINE CHANG AND HER HARDWORKING TEAM.
>> THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR YOUR SUPPORT IN FOSTERING
CROSS-CULTURAL UNDERSTANDING IN OUR CITY AND THE REST
SUMMIT. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES IN THE SUMMER OF
1966 THE TENDERLOIN MUCH LIKE TODAY WAS A CENTER OF CULTURE
AND A HAVEN FOR PEOPLE MARGINALIZED BY SOCIETY.
THE LOCATION OF GENE COMPTON'S CAFETERIA AT THE CORNER OF TURK
AND TAYLOR WAS A PARTICULARLY IMPORTANT THIRD SPACE FOR THE
TRANSGENDER COMMUNITY AT THE TIME.
IN THE 1960S IN SAN FRANCISCO, CROSS-DRESSING WAS ILLEGAL
AND TRANS WOMEN IN PARTICULAR WERE TARGETED BY STAFF AT THE
CAFETERIA AND THE POLICE DEPARTMENT AT THE TIME.
THESE TENSIONS CAME TO A HEAD ONE NIGHT IN AUGUST 1966 WHEN
AFTER A TRANS WOMAN WAS ALMOST ARRESTED SHE FOUGHT BACK,
GALVANIZED THE TRANS COMMUNITY AND THEIR ALLIES.
>> THE VIOLENT CLASHES RECOGNIZES THE BEGINNING OF THE
TRANSGENDER ACTIVISM MOVEMENT IN SAN FRANCISCO AND A
PRECEDENT TO STONEWALL RIOT THREE YEARS LATER IN NEW YORK
CITY. WHILE THE SITE IS RECOGNIZED ON
THE NATIONAL REGISTER OF HISTORIC PLACES, THE FIRST SUCH
PLACE IN THE NATION ASSOCIATED WITH THE TRANSGENDER RIGHTS
MOVEMENT, THE LOCAL LANDMARKING HAS BEEN LIMITED TO THE FACADE
OF THE FIRST FLOOR AND THE STREET IN FRONT OF TRANS
ACTIVISTS AND COMMUNITY LEADERS HAVE BEEN CLEAR THAT THE
LIMITED SCOPE OF THE LOCAL LANDMARKING IS UNACCEPTABLE.
THE BUILDING AT 12121 21 TAYLOR AS A WHOLE REPRESENTS THE POWER
OF THE TRANS MOVEMENT AND THE HISTORY OF RESISTANCE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> THE BUILDING'S CURRENT USE
HAS BEEN A POINT OF DIFFICULTY FOR THE TENDERLOIN COMMUNITY.
IT OPERATES AS A TRANSITIONAL FACILITY UNDER FEDERAL
CONTRACTS OWNED BY GEO GROUP, A PRIVATE PRISON COMPANY THAT
CONTRACTS WITH ICE AND IS AN IMPORTANT ELEMENT OF THE
NATION'S PRISON INDUSTRIAL COMPLEX.
>> LAST YEAR I HELD A HEARING ON THE FACILITY AT TURK
AND TAYLOR AFTER THE PASSING OF MELVIN BALOGUN WHO WAS IN THE
GEO GROUP CUSTODY AT THE TIME OF HIS DEATH.
WE HEARD FROM COMMUNITY MEMBERS THAT WERE FORMERLY RESIDENTS AT
THE SITE ABOUT THE DEPLORABLE CONDITIONS AND AWFUL
MISTREATMENT THAT THEY RECEIVED WITHIN THOSE WALLS.
>> IT'S CLEAR THAT GEO GROUP IS OPERATING THIS BUILDING IN A
WAY THAT IS AT ODDS WITH THE SPIRIT OF FREEDOM OF CIVIL
RIGHTS THAT EMBODIES THE EVENTS THAT TOOK PLACE THERE 60 YEARS
AGO AND POSES A THREAT TO THAT LEGACY.
THAT'S WHY TODAY I'M INTRODUCING LEGISLATION
LEGISLATION TO LANDMARK THE ENTIRE BUILDING THAT CONTAINS
COMPTON CAFETERIA AS A SAN FRANCISCO ARTICLE TEN LANDMARK.
>> THIS EFFORT WAS SHAPED IN CLOSE PARTNERSHIP WITH THE
TURK AND TAYLOR INITIATIVE COMPTON COALITION AND THE
TRANSGENDER DISTRICT WHO HAVE BEEN LEADING DOCUMENTATION,
ADVOCACY AND PRESERVATION WORK FOR YEARS.
COMMUNITY LEADERSHIP FROM THE TRANSGENDER DISTRICT INCLUDING
BRIANNA MCCREE HAS HELPED CENTER THE IMPORTANCE OF
PROTECTING THE FULL BUILDING AS A CONTINUOUS SPACE OF
TRANSGENDER LIFE SURVIVAL, RESISTANCE AND ORGANIZING.
>> WE'RE ALSO GRATEFUL TO COMPTON'S COALITION ESPECIALLY
CHANDLER LABORDE AND THE WORKING GROUP FOR THEIR
LEADERSHIP AND DETAILED POLICY INPUT.
>> WE ALSO THANK DR. SUSAN STRYKER FOR HER FOUNDATIONAL
DOCUMENTATION AND STORYTELLING WORK ON THE COMPTON'S CAFETERIA
UPRISING AND ANDREA HORNE FOR HER CONTINUED ADVOCACY
AND PRESERVING TRANS HISTORY. >> A SPECIAL THANK YOU TO HONEY
MAHOGANY FOR HER EARLY WORK ON THIS PROJECT AND ONGOING
LEADERSHIP TO ADVANCING TRANS EQUITY HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO AS
WELL AS JUPITER PERAZA FOR LAYING MUCH OF THE GROUNDWORK
ON THIS PROJECT. I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR CHEN
FOR YOUR CO-SPONSOR WORSHIP AND THANKS TO PAULA LAVELLE
LAVALLEY AND RICH SEGRE AT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND RENO
COOPER AND WOMACK FOR ON MY TEAM FOR THEIR WORK ON THIS
ITEM. >> NEXT COLLEAGUES FOR A VERY
DIFFERENT KIND OF HISTORY I WANT TO TAKE US BACK TO A LONG
TIME AGO AND A GALAXY FAR, FAR AWAY.
I'M PLEASED TO INTRODUCE A RESOLUTION DECLARING MAY 4TH,
2026 AS STAR WARS DAY FOR THE FIRST TIME IN SAN FRANCISCO
CREATED BY GEORGE LUCAS. STAR WARS IS ONE OF THE MOST
INFLUENTIAL FILM AND TELEVISION FRANCHISES IN HISTORY AND SAN
FRANCISCO'S DEEPLY CONNECTED TO THAT LEGACY.
LUCASFILM IS HEADQUARTERED IN THE PRESIDIO WHERE
INDUSTRIAL LIGHT AND MAGIC CONTINUES TO LEAD INNOVATION
IN FILMMAKING. OUR CITY HAS ALSO HOSTED THE
FIRST PUBLIC SCREENING OF THE ORIGINAL FILM IN 1977 AND TODAY
REMAINS A DESTINATION FOR FANS FROM THE ICONIC YODA FOUNTAIN
TO NEW ATTRACTIONS IN THE PRESIDIO AMIDST THE ACTOR WHO
PORTRAYED JAR JAR BINKS IN THE PHANTOM MENACE WAS DISCOVERED
AT A DANCE PERFORMANCE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AT ITS CORE, STAR WARS IS ABOUT HOPE, RESILIENCE AND THE
PURSUIT OF JUSTICE. VALUES THAT RESONATE STRONGLY
WITH THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO AS CHRIS NEMEC SAYS
ON ANDOR THE PACE OF REPRESSION OUTSTRIPS OUR ABILITY TO
UNDERSTAND IT. >> THE SAGA IS FUNDAMENTALLY
ABOUT THE NEED FOR PERSISTENCE, INGENUITY AND COMING TOGETHER
AS A COMMUNITY TO PUSH BACK AGAINST FORCES THAT THREATEN
OUR WAY OF LIFE SOMETHING I KNOW THAT AS A BOARD AND AS A
CITY GOVERNMENT WE HAVE TO RECKON WITH EVERY DAY.
>> MAY THE 4TH BE WITH YOU. HAS GROWN FROM A FAN DRIVEN
PLAY ON GERRY WELL WISHES AND TO A GLOBAL CELEBRATION.
>> IT'S A TESTAMENT TO THE ENDURING POWER OF THIS STORY
AND THE COMMUNITY THAT SURROUNDS IT.
THIS RESOLUTION RECOGNIZES THAT LEGACY AND INVITES ALL SAN
FRANCISCANS INCLUDING SUPERVISOR MELGAR MYSELF I
THINK ARE THE MAIN STAR WARS NERDS ON THE BOARD TO CELEBRATE
THE IMPACT THAT THIS FRANCHISE HAS HAD ON OUR CULTURE AND OUR
CITY. >> AND IN THE WISE WORDS OF A
SAGE THAT I MASTER MY COLLEAGUES VOTE OR VOTE NOT
THERE IS NO TRY. >> I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR YOUR
SUPPORT. >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
I'VE GOT A FUNNY FEELING ABOUT THIS ONE.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN THANK YOU MADAM CLERK PLEASE ADD ME TO
SUPERVISOR MAHMOUD'S LEGISLATION REGARDING COMPTON'S
CAFETERIA TO THE COMPTON'S CAFETERIA LANDMARKING.
>> I AM SUBMITTING A RESOLUTION RECOGNIZING MAY 26TH AS JEWISH
AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH ON MAY 9TH TO THE 16TH AS SAN
FRANCISCO JEWISH WEEK IN THE CITY COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR YOUR CO-SPONSORSHIP
. I ALSO WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
DORSEY WHO HAS ADDED HIMSELF AS WELL AND LOOK FORWARD TO
DISCUSSING THAT MORE NEXT WEEK. >> TODAY THOUGH I AM ASKING
THAT WE ADJOURN OUR MEETING IN MEMORY OF MICHAEL TILSON
THOMAS ONE OF THE PREEMINENT FIGURES IN 20TH AND 21ST
CENTURY CLASSICAL MUSIC AND THE LONG TIME MUSIC DIRECTOR FOR
THE SAN FRANCISCO SYMPHONY WHO DIED AT HIS HOME SURROUNDED BY
FRIENDS AND FAMILY ON APRIL 22ND AT THE AGE OF 81.
I AM GOING TO ASK THAT UNLESS THERE OBJECTIONS WE DO THIS
IN MEMORIAM ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD.
MICHAEL WAS BORN ON DECEMBER 21ST, 1944 IN LOS ANGELES
AND GREW UP IN A HOUSEHOLD IMMERSED IN MUSICAL PERFORMANCE
AND THEATER. HE BEGAN PLAYING PIANO
AND CONDUCTING AS A TEENAGER AND QUICKLY ROSE TO PROMINENCE
IN LOS ANGELES HELPING PREMIERE WORLD PREMIERE WORKS BY WORLD
FAMOUS COMPOSERS INCLUDING IGOR STRAVINSKY AND AARON COPLAND
AND ACCOMPANYING WORLD-CLASS MUSICIAN MUSICIANS INCLUDING
VIOLINIST YASHA HEIFETZ. MICHAEL CONTINUED STUDYING
MUSIC AT THE UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA'S THORNTON
SCHOOL OF MUSIC AFTER GRADUATING IN 1967.
HE EARNED A CONDUCTING FELLOWSHIP AT TANGLEWOOD THE
THE SUMMER HOME OF THE BOSTON SYMPHONY SYMPHONY.
THERE HE RECOGNIZED HE RECEIVED THE PRESTIGIOUS KOUSSEVITZKY
PRIZE A RECOGNITION THAT LED TO HIM MEETING LEONARD BERNSTEIN
WHO WOULD BECOME A LIFELONG FRIEND AND MENTOR.
IN 1969, AT THE AGE OF 24, HE WAS APPOINTED ASSISTANT
CONDUCTOR OF THE BOSTON SYMPHONY WHERE HE WORKED UNTIL
1970. HE THEN WENT ON TO SERVE AS
MUSIC DIRECTOR FOR THE BUFFALO PHILHARMONIC FOR EIGHT YEARS
AND PRINCIPAL GUEST CONDUCTOR OF THE LOS ANGELES PHILHARMONIC
FOR SEVEN YEARS BEFORE BECOMING THE MUSIC DIRECTOR OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO SYMPHONY IN 1995. MICHAEL GUIDED THE ORCHESTRA
AND NEW DIRECTIONS PAIRING STANDARD REPERTOIRE WITH LESSER
KNOWN WORKS AND EXPERIMENT TO CONTEMPORARY MUSIC.
HE BECAME ESPECIALLY RENOWNED FOR HIS INTERPRETATIONS OF
GUSTAV MAHLER, WHICH CULMINATED IN SEVEN GRAMMY AWARDS
AND INSPIRED A NEW GENERATION OF BAY AREA LISTENERS TO FALL
IN LOVE WITH THE COMPOSER. MICHAEL MADE MAJOR HISTORY AS
ONE OF THE FIRST OPENLY GAY MUSICAL CONDUCTORS OF A MAJOR
ORCHESTRA. HE MET JOSHUA ROBESON IN THEIR
JUNIOR HIGH SCHOOL BAND AND JOSHUA WOULD RECOUNT
IN LATER YEARS HOW HE HEARD MICHAEL DAZZLED FELLOW
CLASSMATES ON THE PIANO. THE TWO REUNITED AND FELL
IN LOVE IN 1976. THEY WOULD BE PERSONAL
AND PROFESSIONAL PARTNERS FOR THE NEXT HALF CENTURY MARRYING
IN 2014. JOSHUA PREDECEASED MICHAEL
IN FEBRUARY OF THIS YEAR AT THE AGE OF 79.
WHEN MICHAEL WAS UNDER CONSIDERATION TO BECOME THE
MUSIC DIRECTOR OF THE SAN FRANCISCO SYMPHONY, HIS
RELATIONSHIP WITH JOSHUA WAS WIDELY KNOWN AND HIS IDENTITY
AS A MAN IN A COMMITTED RELATIONSHIP DID STIR
CONTROVERSY. TO THIS DAY MANY MUSICIANS
CREDIT MICHAEL'S LEADERSHIP WITHIN THE SYMPHONY AND HIS
COMMITMENT TO LIVING OPENLY AND AUTHENTICALLY FOR MAKING IT
EASIER FOR THEM TO COME OUT AND PAVING THE WAY FOR GREATER
INCLUSION OF OPENLY ARTISTS IN CLASSICAL MUSIC.
MICHAEL STEPPED DOWN AS MUSICAL DIRECTOR IN 2020 AND DESPITE
THE COVID 19 PANDEMIC AND LATER BEING DIAGNOSED WITH AN
AGGRESSIVE BRAIN CANCER, MICHAEL CONTINUED TO CONDUCT
RECORD AND TEACH ALL AROUND THE WORLD.
HIS FINAL PUBLIC APPEARANCE WAS ON APRIL 26TH OF LAST YEAR WHEN
HE CONDUCTED THE SAN FRANCISCO SYMPHONY AND A BELATED 80TH
BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION CONCERT. HE DIED IN A SAN FRANCISCO HOME
SURROUNDED BY FAMILY AND FRIENDS.
SAN FRANCISCO ALREADY MISSES HIS BOUNDLESS CREATIVITY,
TALENT AND ENERGY AND HIS LOSS HAS BEEN FELT AROUND THE WORLD.
REST IN PEACE AND POWER MICHAEL TILSON THOMAS.
MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN SUPERVISOR
MELGAR. SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
SAUTER THANK YOU. COLLEAGUES, I HAVE TWO ITEMS TO
INTRODUCE TODAY. FIRST I'M INTRODUCING
LEGISLATION TO ALLOW FOR THE RENEWAL AND EXPANSION OF THE
DOWNTOWN COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT ALSO KNOWN AS DOWNTOWN
S.F. PARTNERSHIP. THIS COMES ONLY AFTER A
SIGNIFICANT GROUNDWORK LAID BY THE DISTRICT OVER THE PAST YEAR
INCLUDING HOURS OF CONVERSATION WITH PROPERTY OWNERS
AND DOWNTOWN STAKEHOLDERS TO REACH THIS POINT.
AN EARLY RENEWAL IS NOT EASY NOR IS IT COMMON.
WE SHOULD TAKE THIS AS A REAL SIGN OF THE TRUST THAT THE
DOWNTOWN PARTNERSHIP HAS BUILT UP AND AN INDICATION OF ITS
AMBITION TO BE AN EVER GREATER STEWARD OF OUR DOWNTOWN SPACES.
THE PARTNERSHIP WAS FORMED IN 2020 AND OF COURSE STARTING
UP IN THE MIDST OF THE PANDEMIC IN WHICH DOWNTOWN WAS IMPACTED
MOST WAS NOT FOR THE FAINT OF HEART.
AND YET THE CBD HAS SHOWN ITS RESILIENCE THROUGH BOTH
ESSENTIAL DAILY SERVICES AROUND SAFETY AND CLEANLINESS
AND CREATIVE NEW PROGRAMS INCLUDING LET'S GO S.F. MARKET
STREET AMBASSADORS AS THE FRONT STREET ENTERTAINMENT ZONE
AND PLACEMAKING AT THE DOWNTOWN GATEWAY MECHANICS MONUMENT
AND THE LANDING AT LIGHTER STAFF.
WITH THIS RENEWAL THE DISTRICT WILL EXPAND FROM ROUGHLY 43 TO
70 BLOCKS, ADDING PORTSIDE FRONTAGE ALONG THE EMBARCADERO.
AND THE RENEWED TERM IS TEN YEARS FROM JANUARY 2027 THROUGH
JUNE THROUGH DECEMBER 2030 SIX. >> MOST IMPORTANTLY, WE'LL SEE
THE IMPACT OF THE RENEWAL WITH AN EXPANSION OF SERVICES MORE
CLEANING NEW OVERNIGHT SAFETY PATROLS AND A STRENGTHENING OF
SMALL BUSINESS SUPPORT AND PUBLIC SPACE PROGRAMING.
THE DOWNTOWN PARTNERSHIP WILL ALSO BE VITAL IN SUPPORTING THE
NEWLY RENOVATED EMBARCADERO PLAZA WHICH WE ARE EXCITED TO
BREAK GROUND ON IN THE NEXT YEAR.
I WANT TO EXPRESS MY THANKS AND APPRECIATION FIRST TO
ROBBIE SILBER, THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE DOWNTOWN S.F.
PARTNERSHIP. ROBBIE IS A STEADY HAND WHO
ALWAYS BALANCES THE TASK AT HAND WITH THE PURSUIT OF A
BIGGER VISION. THANKS AS WELL TO THE ALL OF
THE LEADERSHIP THE DOWNTOWN PARTNERSHIP, ITS BOARD
AND STAKEHOLDERS AS WELL AS CITY DEPARTMENTS PARTICULARLY
THE PORT AND REC IN PART WHO COLLABORATED TO REACH THIS
POINT. FINALLY A BIG THANK YOU TO
JACKIE HAZELWOOD FROM IWD FOR THE INVALUABLE ROLE SHE HAS
PLAYED IN THIS EARLY RENEWAL AND ALL OF THE IMPORTANT
RELATIONSHIPS WITH CBDS ACROSS THE CITY.
>> NEXT TODAY I AM INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO EXPAND SAN
FRANCISCO'S PAID FAMILY LEAVE. >> THIS LEGISLATION WOULD
RESULT IN A TARGETED AND MEANINGFUL EXPANSION BY
ALLOWING MORE EXPECTING PARENTS TO BE ELIGIBLE FOR BENEFITS
AFTER 90 DAYS OF EMPLOYMENT RATHER THAN 180 DAYS.
AS CURRENTLY WRITTEN, WE SHOULDN'T FORCE NEW PARENTS TO
CHOOSE BETWEEN FAMILIES AND THEIR CAREERS.
THIS EXPANSION RESULTS IN MORE NEW PARENTS COVERED STRONGER
FAMILIES ALL WHILE CONTRIBUTING TOWARDS A MORE COMPETITIVE
WORKFORCE. >> THE NUMBERS ARE CLEAR ON THE
IMPACT OF PAID FAMILY LEAVE PARENTS WHO HAVE ACCESS TO IT
EXPERIENCE 30% LOWER LEVELS OF DEPRESSION AND SEE A 10%
DECREASE IN RISK OF POVERTY AND A 4% BOOST IN HOUSEHOLD
INCOME PAID FAMILY LEAVE ALSO CONTRIBUTES TO A STRONG ECONOMY
RESULTING IN A 6% INCREASED RATE OF RETURN TO THE WORKFORCE
AND A LONG TERM IMPROVEMENT IN THE RATE OF LABOR FORCE
DETACHMENT. >> A DECADE AGO SAN FRANCISCO
BECAME THE FIRST MAJOR CITY TO PROVIDE FULLY PAID PARENTAL
LEAVE FOR NEW PARENTS AND THAT WAS GROUNDBREAKING AT THE TIME.
TODAY'S EXPANSION ENSURES WE DO MORE TO SUPPORT YOUNG FAMILIES.
I WANT TO SHARE MY GRATITUDE TO MY INITIAL CO SPONSOR OF THIS
LEGISLATION SUPERVISORS MELGAR WALTON, CHERYL CHEN AND MAHMUD.
A YEAR AGO I BECAME A NEW DAD AND YESTERDAY MY DAUGHTER TOOK
HER FIRST STEPS. THIS JOURNEY IS REWARDING
AND JOYFUL BUT RAISING A YOUNG CHILD IN SAN FRANCISCO ISN'T
EASY AND I SAY THAT AS SOMEONE WITH MEANS AND PRIVILEGE.
THERE ARE TARGETED SPECIFIC WAYS IN WHICH OUR GOVERNMENT
CAN DO MORE TO SUPPORT YOUNG FAMILIES.
SO THAT'S WHY TODAY'S PAID FAMILY LEAVE EXPANSION IS ONLY
THE BEGINNING OF MY FOCUS TO MAKE IT EASIER TO RAISE A YOUNG
FAMILY IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> THIS EFFORT SUPPORTING
TOMORROW'S RESIDENTS WITH OPPORTUNITY, LIVABILITY
AND LEARNING EDUCATION AND RESOURCES WHICH THANKFULLY
SHORTEN'S CONVENIENTLY TO THE STROLLER ACT WILL INCLUDE
MULTIPLE INITIATIVES TO SHAPE SAN FRANCISCO TO BECOME MORE
FRIENDLY, ACCESSIBLE AND AFFORDABLE TO THOSE RAISING
YOUNG FAMILIES. >> THROUGH THE STROLLER ACT WE
WILL SEEK TO EXPAND ACCESS TO DIAPER CHANGING TABLES
AND BUILDINGS, STRENGTHENING STRENGTHEN LEGISLATION TO
SUPPORT NURSING MOTHERS, NURSING MOTHERS IN THE
WORKPLACE MAKE PUBLIC TRANSIT MORE ACCESSIBLE TO FAMILIES,
SPEED UP NEW CURB RAMPS AND SIDEWALK REPAIRS AND ENSURE
PATHWAYS TO LEARNING ARE AVAILABLE FOR ALL.
SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENTS. THANK YOU TO MY CHIEF OF STAFF
TITA BELL FOR ALL OF HER PARTNERSHIP TO BRING THIS
FORWARD. THANK YOU AS WELL TO MAUREEN
SLACK IN THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE.
AND THANK YOU TO THE MAYOR AND DEPARTMENT ON THE STATUS OF
WOMEN FOR THEIR SUPPORT OF THIS LEGISLATION AND THE REST OF IT.
>> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR SAUTER.
MR. PRESIDENT, THERE ARE NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER.
>> THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. YOU NEED ME TO GAVEL DOWN ON MY
REQUEST TO DO THE MTA ON BEHALF OF THE FULL BOARD.
>> THAT WOULD BE IN ORDER. LET'S DO THAT WITHOUT
OBJECTION. ALL RIGHT.
>> LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL. >> I'M NOT ROLL CALL UP BUT A
PUBLIC COMMENT? YES.
SO AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT.
IF YOU WOULDN'T MIND LINING UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE
CHAMBER. >> YOU'LL BE ABLE TO SPEAK TO
THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED. WHETHER OR NOT THE BOARD SHOULD
GO INTO CLOSED SESSION THAT'S ITEM 43 TO DISCUSS THE VARIOUS
ITEMS WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE.
ITEMS 44 THROUGH 47 THE ITEMS UP FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE AND OTHER GENERAL MATTERS NOT ON THE
PUBLISHED AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER
JURISDICTION. I WILL JUST STATE FOR THE
RECORD THAT THERE ARE THERE ARE NO PUBLIC COMMENTS ASSOCIATED
WITH ANY ELECTIONEERING. AS WE'RE NEARING AN ELECTION
AND I WILL TAKE THE FIRST CALL I'M SORRY WE'LL TAKE THE FIRST
SPEAKER. >> WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES. WELCOME.
>> THAT TWEET. I DON'T SURE IS YOU SO TO
CONFIRM OR ADEQUATELY FUND DR. BLOCK DISABILITY.
I KNOW CONTINUUM IS OSCAR DE LA DANIEL.
>> WELL I LOVE SOLAR NOUVEAU CYCLE AKEELAH BASSETT
. >> MERCI.
>> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
WELCOME. ALL RIGHT.
GOOD AFTERNOON. >> DENISE LEWIS SPEAKING UP.
AS YOU MAY KNOW FROM PREVIOUS COMMUNICATIONS, I'M A LONGTIME
ADVOCATE FOR FIRE PREVENTION AND PREPAREDNESS AND FOR NATIVE
BIODIVERSITY. IN MY APRIL SECOND EMAIL TO YOU
I ASKED FOR DISCUSSION OR BOARD RESOLUTION AND ORDINANCE OR
CHARTER REFORM REGARDING SEVEN ISSUES.
THE TOP THREE INCLUDE PROVIDING FOR PRIORITIZING PUBLIC SAFETY
ESPECIALLY WITH RESPECT TO FIRE PREVENTION AND PREPAREDNESS
AND THUS PRIORITIZE RAISING OUR BUDGETS.
SECONDLY, WE NEED A VEGETATION MANAGEMENT PLAN THAT ADDRESSES
VEGETATIVE FUEL REDUCTION TO MITIGATE WILDFIRE RISK AND TO
FOCUS ON PLANTING INDIGENOUS PLANTS.
THIRDLY, TO HOLD THE PUC ACCOUNTABLE FOR EXPANDING THE
EMERGENCY FIREFIGHTING WATER SYSTEM TO ALL UNPROTECTED
NEIGHBORHOODS BY 2034. THESE ISSUES ARE ALIGNED WITH
YOUR PRIOR WILDFIRE HEARINGS IN 2015, 2019 AND 2021 WITH
YOUR 2018 BIODIVERSITY RESOLUTION AND WITH YOUR 2019
DECLARATION OF A STATE OF URGENCY FOR A FULL BUILD OUT OF
THE EMERGENCY FIREFIGHTING ORDER SYSTEM.
I URGE YOU TO TAKE MY SEVEN SUGGESTIONS SERIOUSLY AND SINCE
THE LAND USE COMMITTEE DID OR DID NOT OR DOES NOT ALLOW
PUBLIC COMMENT AT THEIR MEETINGS, I NOW REQUEST THAT
THOSE OF YOU WHO ARE MEMBERS HOLD ANOTHER WILDFIRE
PREVENTION AND PREPAREDNESS HEARING OR WORKSHOP OF COURSE
WITH PUBLIC PARTICIPATION. I'D EVEN LIKE TO MAKE A
PRESENTATION. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI. MY NAME IS RICHARD JOHNSON
AND I'M SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF HIV SAFE.
I HAVE OVER THREE DECADES OF COMMUNITY SERVICE EXPERIENCE
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND BY FAR THAT DISMISSAL
AND UNWILLINGNESS TO HEAR FROM ALL CONSTITUENTS THAT I HAVE
WITNESSED OVER THE LAST YEAR HAS NEVER BEEN SO DAMNING.
AFTER TRYING FOR AN ENTIRE QUARTER AT THE START OF HIS
TENURE LAST, YOUR SUPERVISOR MAHMUD HAS DEMONSTRATED
EXCLUSIONARY ENGAGEMENT WHICH WE OUTLINED IN FORMAL NOTICES
TO CITY HALL NOTICES. HE HAS BEEN A RECIPIENT OF A
FEW. A FEW DAYS LEADING UP TO THE
RECENT SFO MTA ESCORT HEARING SUPERVISOR MARTIN WHOSE OFFICE
ACTIVELY COORDINATED WITH THE UNION.
IT IS A LETTER OF SUPPORT FOR THE FARMERS MARKET PROPOSAL ONE
THAT HE DID NOT ENGAGE THE BROADER NEIGHBORHOOD OR
STAKEHOLDERS ON AND WHICH WILL LAYER ANOTHER YEAR LONG CLOSURE
ON TOP OF A PERMIT ALREADY UNDER FORMAL ADMINISTRATIVE
COMPLAINT WITH S.F. MTA. IT'S AWFUL THAT A FARMER'S
MARKET THAT COULD GARNER CONSENSUS AT THE RIGHT LOCATION
IS BEING FAST TRACKED TO ENTRENCH A CONTESTED CLOSURE
IN THE FINAL HOUR DOCUMENT DUMP FROM THE RECENT COURT ACTION BY
THE PERMIT HOLDER. WE LEARNED THAT SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD HAD ALREADY INFORMED IN HP AN APRIL NUMBER THAT HE
WAS OUTRIGHT DECLINING TO MEET WITH US.
A SUPERVISOR WHO FEELS COMFORTABLE IGNORING LEGITIMATE
CONSTITUENT CONCERNS FROM A SIX YEAR OLD NEIGHBORHOOD ADVOCACY
GROUP IS SENDING A DANGEROUS SIGNAL WHEN A SUPERVISOR KNOWS
A CONSTITUENT IT SETS THE TONE FOR EVERY DEPARTMENT UNDER HIM
TO DO THIS SAME. LEADERSHIP REQUIRES SETTING THE
STANDARD ON THIS ISSUE. SUPERVISOR MAHMUD HAS FAILED AT
THAT LEVEL. SUPERVISOR CHERYL I THANK YOU
FOR ACKNOWLEDGING. >> CAN YOU KEEP YOUR COMMENTS
TO THE BOARD AS A WHOLE? IT IS AS A WHOLE WHEN YOU SPOKE
TO SUPERVISOR CHERYL DIRECTLY TELL THE WHOLE BOARD WHAT YOUR
THOUGHTS ARE ON SUPERVISOR CHERYL.
>> OKAY. I MY WHOLE THOUGHTS ON THIS
SITUATION WAS IN A RECENT ACTIVITY WITH TWO SUPERVISORS
THAT WERE IN PRESENCE. I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE
SUPERVISOR CHERYL AND GREETING ME AND BEING CIVIL TO ME.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> DANIELLE SPILLMAN WAS A TRANS ELDER WHO WAS MURDERED BY
A MAN IN A MACHINE WHO CLAIMS HE FEARED FOR HIS AND HIS
FAMILY'S LIFE DESPITE BEING IN THIS MACHINE WITH THE PROVEN
ABILITY TO KILL THIS 74 YEAR OLD WOMAN.
BY ALL ACCOUNTS, DANIELLE WAS GENTLE AND KIND, COMPASSIONATE
AND GIVING. SHE DESERVED TO PASS PEACEFULLY
NATURALLY SOME DAY FAR OFF INTO THE FUTURE AND THIS MAN STOLE
THAT FOR HER FROM HER. >> FOR DANIELLE GENTLE KIND
ABUSED. >> TARGETED.
DISPLACED. TALENTED TRANS.
THERE ARE NO PROMISES FOR TRANS PEOPLE SO WE CAN'T SAY ANY
PROMISES WERE BROKEN. THERE WAS NEVER A PROMISE OF
LOVE AND SAFETY. NO PROMISE OF A DIGNIFIED LIFE
AND DEATH. SO NONE WERE BROKEN WHEN SHE
WAS RUN DOWN BY A HATEFUL MAN AND A LARGE MACHINE MOWED HER
LIKE A FRAGILE DAISY REACHING FOR THE SUN ON AN URBAN MEADOW
OF CONCRETE AND PAVEMENTS TORN ASUNDER NOT BY BROKEN PROMISES
TORN ASUNDER TORN FROM LOVE FILLED FRIENDSHIPS AND GENTLE
CREATURES TORN BY A KEPT PROMISE TO ERADICATE US.
>> ALSO AS A TRANSGENDER MEXICAN-AMERICAN I LEFT MY JOB
AT THE SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS BECAUSE TRUMP'S IN-LAW JOSHUA
KUSHNER BOUGHT A STAKE IN THE TEAM.
>> THE LINE IS TOO DIRECT BETWEEN MY LOW WAGE LABOR TO
THE TRUMP FAMILY FORTUNE TO THE REGIME MURDERING HUMANS
GLOBALLY TO THE MASKED MEN KIDNAPING US, DISAPPEARING US
TORTURING US AND LITTLE CHILDREN TEARING HUMANS APART.
PSYCHOLOGY HIGHLY EMOTIONALLY PHYSICALLY ACROSS BORDERS
IN TORTURE ROOMS SOMETIMES UNTIL DEATH INCREASINGLY
TOWARDS DEATH. >> TO THE BILLIONAIRES LIKE
JOSHUA KUSHNER WHO TARGET AND SCAPEGOAT THE MOST
MARGINALIZED THE LEAST PROTECTED THE LINE IS TO DIRECT
THE SAME BILLIONAIRES EXECUTING A TRANSGENDER GENOCIDE IN THIS
COUNTRY TO THE DEATHLESS DESTRUCTION OF OUR INSTITUTIONS
OF EDUCATION, SCIENCE, HEALTH CARE AND ALL EFFORTS TOWARD
SOCIAL JUSTICE. >> ALL HISTORY.
ALL HONEST HISTORY REBURYING OUR PAST IN UNMARKED GRAVES.
I LEFT MY JOB AT THE SAN FRANCISCO SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS
BECAUSE THEY ASKED ME TO SHOVEL YOUR GRAVE TOO.
>> IN MY PERSONAL OPINION, GOP DEMOCRAT NO LABELS ALL
BILLIONAIRES ARE INCOMPREHENSIBLY EXTREME
HOARDERS HIDING AND CONTROLLING AN EXTREMELY DISPROPORTIONATE
AMOUNT OF ALL OUR RESOURCES AND THE VAST ENTIRETY OF THE
HUMAN SPECIES IS SUFFERING FOR IT.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> ALL RIGHT. HI EVERYONE.
MY NAME IS CAITLIN. I'M JUST GOING TO SAY THAT I
THINK TWO MINUTES THIS SHOULD BE LONGER FOR THE PUBLIC.
I FEEL LIKE IT'S VERY LITTLE TIME BUT I ALSO THINK THAT JUST
TO INTRODUCE MYSELF A BIT I ONLY THINK THIS COUNTRY HAS
BEEN BUILT WITH ME IN MIND. NORD THIS BUILDING IN HERE HAS
THIS SO CALLED COUNTRY OR THIS BUILDING HAS BEEN BUILT WITH ME
IN MIND AND THEN I JUST WANTED TO SAY THAT I AM A PERSON
LIVING IN THIS CITY RENT AND PAID FOR MORE THAN FIVE
YEARS NOR BILLS AND THE GE IS WEIRDLY STRUCTURED IN THE SENSE
THAT WHILE IT'S COMING AFTER ME TO ASK ME IF I HAVE ANY SORT OF
A CHANGE IN MY FINANCIAL SITUATION SO THEY CAN CUT ME
OFF EVEN FROM THAT EVEN THOUGH I HAVE NO INCOME THEY ALSO
REQUIRE ME TO REPORT IF I MAKE ANY INCOME SO THERE IS NO TRUST
BECAUSE THEY IT WORKS WELL EITHER YOU WAIT FOR ME TO BRING
YOU WHEN I HAVE INCOME AND YOU TRUST ME OR YOU CONTINUOUSLY
COME AFTER ME TO ASK ME. SO THAT NEEDS RESTRUCTURING
IN MY VIEW AND THEN TO I AM SADDENED THAT YOU GUYS SEEM TO
SUPPORT COMPETITIVE SPORTS WHICH REALLY I THINK ARE VERY
DETRIMENTAL. I LOVE SPORTS.
I LOVE SPORTS NOT COMPETITIVE SPORTS NOT COMPETITIVE SPORTS.
SO I LOVE EXERCISING BUT I'M NOT FOR COMPETITION SO THAT I
HOPE YOU GUYS HAVE HEARD ME AND YOU KNOW I GOT FIVE
SECONDS. I'M JUST GOING TO LEAVE IT
THERE FOR NOW. THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR
LISTENING TO ME. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME YOUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS JESSE ROLLINS AND I'M HERE REPRESENTING THE
TENDERLOIN NEIGHBORHOOD DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION AS A
MEMBER OF THE SUPPORTIVE HOUSING PROVIDERS NETWORK TDC
IS THE LARGEST AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPER AND OUR
AGENCY OWNS THE MOST SUPPORTIVE HOUSING UNITS IN SAN FRANCISCO
. >> SO TODAY I'M HERE TO SUPPORT
RECOVERY, HOUSING AND REQUEST YOUR SUPPORT FOR TWO AMENDMENTS
TO FILE NUMBER 251003 THE DRUG FREE HOUSING LEGISLATION.
>> FIRST WE WOULD SUPPORT CHANGES THAT WOULD PREVENT
EVICTIONS BASED SOLELY ON SUBSTANCE USE OR RELAPSE
RECOGNIZING THERE ARE CERTAIN BEHAVIORS THAT CAN CO-OCCUR
WITH DRUG USE THAT ARE THE PROBLEM AND ALLOW TENANTS WHO
NEED TO MOVE OUT OF RECOVERY HOUSING TO REMAIN HOUSED WHILE
AN ALTERNATIVE HOUSING PLACEMENT IS IDENTIFIED OR
ALLOW A PERSON TO RETURN TO THEIR UNIT IF SEEKING OUTSIDE
MEDICAL CARE. >> SECONDLY, WE URGE REMOVE
REMOVING THE BAN ON NEW SUPPORTIVE HOUSING FUNDING
AND TO INSTEAD DO A PRIORITIZATION OF LOCAL FUNDING
FOR RECOVERY HOUSING TO DO RECOVERY HOUSING WE DON'T NEED
TO ELIMINATE ALL OTHER HOUSING MODELS QUITE SIMPLY WE CAN DO
BOTH. >> LASTLY, SUPPORTIVE HOUSING
IS NOT DRUG TOLERANT PCH UNDER FIRST HOUSING ALREADY OPERATES
WITH LEASES THAT PROHIBIT ONSITE ILLICIT DRUG USE
AND ALLOW EVICTIONS BASED ON ILLICIT DRUG USE WHEN
ACCOMPANIED BY LEASE VIOLATIONS.
>> ACCOMPLISHING RECOVERY HOUSING IS POSSIBLE.
LET'S DO IT WITHOUT BANNING ALL OTHER HOUSING AND ENSURE OUR
HOUSING DOESN'T REINFORCE THE PUNITIVE PARADIGM THAT WOULD DE
FACTO INCREASE HOMELESSNESS AND PUBLIC DRUG CONSUMPTION.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER AND GOOD AFTERNOON.
I AM HERE TO EXPOSE A SYSTEMIC PROCESS OF ENGINEERED EXCLUSION
TARGETING MINORITY PROFESSIONALS WITHIN THE HSA
H.R. DEPARTMENT.
I AM NOT AN OBSERVER. I AM THE EVIDENCE MY ENTRY INTO
THE SYSTEM REQUIRED PASSING MULTIPLE EXAMS DESPITE
POSSESSING ADVANCED CREDENTIALS THE INITIAL BARRIER ONCE INSIDE
I DISCOVERED THE SYSTEM'S TRUE DESIGN FOR EXCLUSION NURTURE BY
THE DIRECTOR OF HSA AT THE TIME LEWIN AKIN AND THE OPERATIONAL
MANAGER DAVID TOO. I PERSONALLY WITNESSED A TWO
TIER TRAINING SYSTEM THAT FUNNELS QUALIFIED MINORITY
PROFESSIONALS INTO GROTESQUE SUBPAR UNSTRUCTURED HOLDING
CELLS WHILE A PREFERRED GROUP IS GIVEN STRUCTURE PATHWAYS
THAT GUARANTEES THEIR CAREER SUCCESS.
THIS PROFESSIONAL DIVIDE IS ENFORCED BY MANAGERIAL
OVERRIDES THAT OFTENTIMES BYPASS MERIT ENTIRELY.
LEE WHEN EXCELLENCE IS REJECTED FOR A PREFERRED CANDIDATE, THE
RESULTING DEMOGRAPHICS ARE NOT ACCIDENTAL.
THEY ARE ENGINEERED THROUGH DISCRETIONARY EXCLUSION.
THE MOST PROFOUND TRAIT PORTRAYAL WAS THE STRATEGIC
CO-OPTION OF MY INTELLECT ACTUAL LABOR, MY DEBATES WITH
THE DIRECTOR OF HSA H.R. LUELLA KIM FOR RACIAL EQUITY WERE USED
AS A DUST DEPOSITION TO EXTRACT EXTRACT MY EXPERT BLUEPRINTS MY
SPECIFIC STRATAGEMS WERE HARVESTED REBRANDED AS A NEW
INTERNAL INITIATIVE CALLED EIB AND HANDED TO ACER KEY TO
MANAGE. I WAS THEN DENIED THE ACCESS
TRAINING AND THE RIGHT TO MANAGE THE VERY DEPARTMENT WHO
IDEAS I AUTHORED IN THIS SYSTEM BETRAYAL WAS REWARDED WITH
PROMOTIONS. I WAS MET WITH A MULTI-YEAR
COMMUNICATION BLACKOUT AND ULTIMATELY FORCED INTO A
SEPARATION A MEDICAL SEPARATION WITHOUT EVEN A PERFORMANCE
REVIEW. >> I HAVE TRIED.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS, MA'AM.
THANK YOU KINDLY. WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES FOR EVERYONE. I'LL MAKE AN ANNOUNCEMENT.
WE HAVE TWO MORE SPEAKERS IN LINE IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO
ADDRESS THE BOARD TODAY PLEASE LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND
SIDE. >> WELCOME, SIR.
HELLO. OH, I DON'T KNOW IF YOU CAN
HEAR ME. MY NAME IS DR. MILLER.
I'M HERE ONCE AGAIN BEFORE THE BOARD.
I'VE BEEN HERE NUMEROUS TIMES. I'VE HAD THE PLEASURE OF
MEETING WITH WITH NUMEROUS OF YOU INDIVIDUALS AND I
APPRECIATE YOUR HELP. >> HOWEVER, I'M HERE AGAIN TO
ASK FOR SOME ASSISTANCE. I THINK THE CITY ALTHOUGH WE
HAVE COMPLEX ISSUES IN REGARDS TO THE HOMELESS AND THE DRUG
ADDICTION ISSUES WE NEED, THERE'S AN URGENCY THAT I'M NOT
SEEN BY THE CITY TO TAKE CARE OF THESE ISSUES IN CERTAIN
NEIGHBORHOODS. ONE NEIGHBORHOOD WHERE I HAVE
LIVED AND WORKED FOR MANY YEARS IS THE LOWER POLK STREET AREA
NEAR THE HOSPITAL WHICH I'M SURE YOU'RE ALL AWARE OF LOWER
POLK STREET AND LARKIN THAT AREA HAS BEEN A DRUG
CONTAINMENT ZONE NOW FOR WAY TOO LONG TO MY THE IMPETUS TO
COME HERE TODAY WAS I WAS JUST I WENT OUT TODAY AND JUST ON MY
WAY HERE I COUNTED OVER 50 INDIVIDUALS OPENLY TAKING DRUGS
. THIS IS JUST NOT ACCEPTABLE AT
THIS POINT IN THIS CITY AND I'M NOT HERE TO SHAME ANY PERSON
BUT I'VE MET SAM DODGE. THESE PEOPLE ARE WORKING
DILIGENTLY HARD THESE PEOPLE NEED HELP AND ASSISTANCE.
IT'S A VERY COMPLEX ISSUE. BUT IN THIS DAY AND AGE AFTER
STARTING MY ADVOCACY FOR THESE PEOPLE NOT ONLY BY TAKING CARE
OF THEM FOR 30 YEARS BUT ALSO BY MEETING WITH MR. LEE WHEN HE
WAS THE MAYOR HERE AND STARTED THIS WHO WAS SO KIND TO MEET
WITH ME. THIS IS WHEN THIS THIS PROBLEM
HAS BEEN GOING ON FOR WAY TOO LONG BILLIONS OF DOLLARS HAVE
BEEN SPENT BY NONPROFITS, BY DIFFERENT PEOPLE.
WE NEED MUCH MORE OVERSIGHT AND I'M REALLY REQUESTING THAT
ALL OF YOU FROM THE BOARD OF BOARD OF SUPERVISORS GET
TOGETHER NOT JUST BY YOUR DISTRICT BUT START LOOKING AT
OTHER DISTRICTS AND NOT PUSH YOUR TO EACH OTHER DISTRICT
IN PARTICULAR THIS IS DISTRICT FIVE IN DISTRICT THREE WHICH
ARE REALLY BEEN HIT HARD AND I THINK WE ALL NEED TO JOIN AS A
COMMUNITY AND THE SEGREGATION NOT MY DISTRICT THAT'S THEIR
DISTRICT. WE ALL ARE RESPONSIBLE AND WE
ALL HAVE A RESPONSIBLE TO TAKE CARE OF EACH OTHER.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS YOUR NOW THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> MY NAME IS RICHARD SD PETERSON AND TO BOARD PRESIDENT
RANDLEMAN AND THE REST OF THE BOARD I UNDERSTAND YOU'RE GOING
TO HAVE A CLOSED SESSION SOON WHERE YOU'RE GOING TO BE
TALKING WITH THE ATTORNEYS AND I HOPE DURING THIS MEETING
CERTAIN ISSUES ISSUES WILL BE BROUGHT UP SUCH AS THE
CONTINUED ABSENCE OF DISTRICT NINE SUPERVISOR SAN FRANCISCO
POLITICS WAS ONCE DESCRIBED BY I BELIEVE CHOU AS A KNIFE FIGHT
IN A PHONE BOOTH. >> WELL, YOU KNOW, SOMETIMES IT
IS AND SOMETIMES IT'S NOT. SOMETIMES THE SUPERVISORS ARE
VERY AGGRESSIVE AND PERHAPS MAKING A LEGISLATURE AND A
LEGISLATURE THAT IS NOT TIRED ENTIRELY UNDERSTANDABLE
REGARDING A FORMER SUPERVISOR SIMPLY TO KEEP HIM FROM RUNNING
AGAIN THAT'S KIND OF PETTY BUT CURRENTLY THE MORE IMPORTANT
THING IS INVESTING GATION AND CENSURE OF THE SUPERVISORS
AND FROM DISTRICT NINE WHICH SHOULD BE DISCUSSED BECAUSE THE
WORD OF TODAY IS COMPLICITY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
THANK YOU, FELICIA ROCHELLE BABY BONUS POINT COORDINATING
COUNCIL WONDERFUL TO BE IN THE CHAMBER AGAIN.
>> I DO NOT KNOW HOW ALL OF THIS WORKS SOMETIMES AND I'M
HERE TO SPEAK ON THE FACT THAT I'M IN THE SPIRIT OF SHARON
HEWETT OH ONE OF MY MENTORS PRAISE HER NAME FOR BEING SUCH
A GREAT WOMAN OF OF STRENGTH AND COURAGE AND LOOKED OUT FOR
THE COMMUNITY. SO I AM A BABY RESIDENT NATIVE
SAN FRANCISCAN AND I'M NOT SURE IF I CAN TRUST MY AIR QUALITY
WHO I GO TO THE CAC MEETINGS AND THERE IS SOME CONVERSATION
GOING ON BETWEEN THE SHIPYARD, THE NAVY AND THE RESIDENTS
AND THE THE BOARD THAT'S THERE, THE OVERSEERS THERE OF IT I CAN
NOT TRUST THE PROCESS. >> THAT'S ALL I'M SAYING.
I WOULD LOVE TO BUT IS HARD TO BELIEVE THE NAVY THEY DID SAY
THAT THEY HAVE A THIRD PARTY OR WHAT HAVE YOU MONITORING
AND THEN THEY TALKED ABOUT MONITORING LAST NIGHT ABOUT
JUST HOW THE SAMPLES CAN BE YOU KNOW, NOT TAMPERED BUT ELEVATED
LEVELS READ BECAUSE THE MACHINERY MAY NOT BE CLEAN OR
WHATEVER, WHATEVER THE BOTTOM LINE IS IT'S TOXIC.
>> ALL OF THIS MISHANDLED ALL OF THAT IS SOME SCARY FOR SOME
LIFE THREATENING FOR ALL AND WE ALL NEED TO BE TESTED HONESTLY
ESPECIALLY IN BAYVIEW. WE ALL NEED TO BE TESTED.
SO HOW CAN THAT HAPPEN? WHAT IS THIS VOICE OF MINE
DOING ON THIS MIKE RIGHT NOW TO THE EARS OF THOSE WHO ARE
LISTENING. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
I'LL PRAISE AND GLORY BE TO THE ALMIGHTY CREATOR OF HEAVENS
AND EARTH MY NAME IS JUSTICE AND I AM A DESCENDANT OF THE
INDIGENOUS TRIBE OF THE RAMA. TO THAT YOU TALK ABOUT AS YOU
KNOW THE ELDERS AND CHIEF SPEAK AND SAY OUR DESCENDANTS ARE
BLACK. >> I WANT TO SPEAK ABOUT MANY
OF THE EVENTS THAT'S TALKED ABOUT.
I CAME AND HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO BE PRESENT AT AN EVENT HERE
AT THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND THERE'S A LOT OF TALK ABOUT
JEWISH EVENTS AND I WANT THE AUDACITY TO BE PURE AND SAY WE
RECOGNIZE OUR HEBREW. THE MEXICAN PRESIDENT SAID
WE'RE GOING TO ACKNOWLEDGE INDIGENOUS PEOPLE AND AFRO
INDIGENOUS PEOPLE SO I WANT SAN FRANCISCO WHICH HAVE ALWAYS
BEEN A PILLAR AND DOING THINGS FIRST TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE BLACK
HEBREW PEOPLE WOULD THAT BEING SAID THERE'S MUCH HAS BEEN SAID
HERE WITH MANY OF THE SUPERVISORS GOOD AND NOT SO
GOOD. I WILL MAKE AN EFFORT TO
CONTACT EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU ALL TO HOPE IN HOPES THAT
YOU GUYS MAKE CONTACT AND KEEP COMMUNICATION OPEN.
>> THERE'S A PROGRAM THAT I HAVE WRITTEN AND POLICY THAT I
HAVE PREPARED. I HAVE SENT EMAILS OUT AND I
HOPE THAT YOU GUYS GET THEM. I HOLD NO QUARREL OR NO
POSITION NOT TO WORK WITH ANYONE UNLESS THEY DO NOT
ACKNOWLEDGE TRUTH. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
IF THERE ARE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS PLEASE LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT
HAND SIDE OTHERWISE THIS MAY BE OUR LAST SPEAKER WELCOME
AND I'LL JUST REMIND THE SPEAKER THERE IS NO CAMPAIGNING
THIS AFTERNOON. >> THANK YOU BIBLE TO PUT A MAN
CAN YOU SPEAK DIRECTLY INTO THAT MICROPHONE SO WE CAN HEAR
YOU BEST? THANK YOU.
>> YES. AM I ABLE TO PUT A CLIP ON YOUR
QUESTION OF A VIDEO? >> YES, YOU CAN PLAY A VIDEO IF
YOU ARE PREPARED TO PLAY IT IN YOUR TWO MINUTES.
>> I'M GOING TO SET THE TIMER NOW AND IT SHOULD BE AN
APPROPRIATE VIDEO. >> YEAH.
OKAY. >> HERE'S WHAT I WANTED TO SAY
ORIGINALLY LAST TIME. >> I'M STARTING YOUR TWO
MINUTES NOW SO THE YOUTH COMMISSION THEY WANTED THERE
WAS A SIX HOUR VOTE TO GET US. SURE.
ALL RIGHT. SURE.
COMPANIES MAKE SURE COMPANIES TO GET HELMETS FOR OKAY.
THIS IS AN EXACT COPY. LET ME SHOW YOU THE ONE OF MY
EMAIL BUT MAN PLEASE USE THE MICROPHONE SO THE PUBLIC CAN
HEAR YOU. YES, I AM SORRY ABOUT THAT.
I'M TRYING MY BEST. I AM TRYING TO DO SIX THINGS AT
ONE TIME AND HE IS RIGHT OR SOMEBODY WAS RIGHT.
THERE IS NOT ENOUGH TIME FOR TWO MINUTES FOR PUBLIC COMMENTS
IF THERE'S AN EASIER WAY FOR US TO DO PUBLIC COMMENTS
BEFOREHAND. ALSO IF I UNDERSTAND THERE'S AN
ARGUMENT AGAINST STREAMLINING THE CHARTER BUT WE DO HAVE TO
CONSOLIDATE SOME MEETINGS AT TIMES WHEN I'M GOING TO
MEETINGS YESTERDAY FOR EXAMPLE I WENT TO THREE MEETINGS AT ONE
TIME AND THAT'S A LOT OF CONFLICTING MEETINGS.
IT WAS THE HOUSING STABILITY FUND AT THE SAME TIME AS THE
YOUTH COMMISSION FUND AT THE SAME TIME AS THE SORRY THERE
WAS ANOTHER MEETING AT THE SAME TIME IT WAS THE SMALL
BUSINESSES ON COMMISSION AND THEN PRIOR TO THAT WAS THE
ONE FOR THE FILM AND THAT ONE IT WAS HARD TO EVEN GET ACCESS
TO WHAT THE AGENDA ITEMS WERE SAME AS THE UH THE FUNDING FOR
THE HOUSING I BELIEVE I HAD TO DOUBLE CHECK THAT I SAW RIGHT
IN THE PUBLIC COMMENT BUT I JUST DIDN'T KNOW IF IT WAS
EASILY ACCESSIBLE. >> OH THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. ARE THERE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS TO
ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED AND WE'RE GOING TO SKIP OVER
OUR CLOSED SESSION FOR NOW WHICH WE WILL TAKE UP AT THE
END OF OUR AGENDA. SO MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU
PLEASE CALL OUR FOR ADOPTION OF THAT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA
ITEMS 44 THROUGH 47 ITEMS 44 THROUGH 47 WERE INTRODUCED FOR
ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS
REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING ANY
MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TO GO TO
COMMITTEE. >> I DON'T SEE ANYBODY ON THE
ROSTER. MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE FOUR ASSIGNMENT WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE AGENDA ON ITEMS 44 THROUGH 47 SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG
WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN EYE MANDALAY MAN EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR EYE AND SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR
EITHER ARE TONIGHT WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR
CLOSED SESSION ITEM PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 43.
>> ITEM 40 THREE IS THE CLOSED SESSION WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY
IN CONFERENCE WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY ON EXISTING
LITIGATION. THIS CLOSED SESSION WAS
SCHEDULED PURSUANT TO A MOTION NUMBER M 20 6-040 CONTAINED
IN FILE NUMBER 260410 APPROVED ON APRIL 21ST 2026.
THIS CLOSED SESSION IS FOR THE PURPOSE OF CONFERRING WITH OR
RECEIVING ADVICE FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY REGARDING VARIOUS
EXISTING LITIGATION MATTERS IN WHICH THE CITY IS A PARTY.
>> ALL RIGHT TO THE MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WE ARE GOING TO ASK
THAT YOU EXIT THE CHAMBER WHILE WE GO INTO CLOSED SESSION WILL
RESUME THE MEETING IN OPEN SESSION AFTER WE CONCLUDE.
>> MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE LET US KNOW WHEN THE
CHAMBER IS READY? >> YES.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. WE WILL PREPARE THE CHAMBER
S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
AND S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION SYSTEM
AS
S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
LA
S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENTAL DIVISION
S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION RADIO TWO
GAVELS OR ONE GAVEL BE BACK WE'RE BACK.
WE'RE BACK. ALL RIGHT COLLEAGUES WE ARE
BACK IN OPEN SESSION NO ACTION WAS TAKEN IN CLOSED SESSION.
CAN I HAVE A MOTION OF THE BOARD'S FINE.
THE BOARD FINDS THAT IT'S IN THE BEST INTEREST OF THE
PUBLIC THAT THE BOARD ELECTED NOT TO DISCLOSE ITS CLOSED
SESSION DELIBERATIONS MOVED BY CHAN SECONDED BY SOTTO OR MADAM
CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION NOT TO
DISCLOSE? SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MARK I
SUPERVISOR AMANDA LEMON RANDLEMAN EYES SUPERVISOR
MILKER MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUDER EITHER ATTORNEYS
WITHOUT OBJECTION WE WILL NOT DISCLOSE OUR CLOSED SESSION
DELIBERATIONS AND SEEING NO OTHER NAMES ON THE ROSTER.
>> THIS CLOSED SESSION HAS BEEN HELD AND IS NOW FILED.
>> MADAM CLERK DO YOU HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
THERE ARE NONE TO REPORT. >> MR. PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU
PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM? TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR THE LATE MR. DWAYNE GAINES,
SENIOR AND ON A MOTION MADE BY PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN TO BE ON
BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD ON BEHALF FOR MICHAEL TILSON
THOMAS. THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA.
DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK WE ARE ADJOURNED